<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief declaration of the Lords Supper with some other determinations and disputations concerning the same argument by the same author / written by Dr. Nicholas Ridley, Bishop of London during his imprisonment ; to which is annexed an extract of several passages to the same purpose out of a book intituled Diallacticon, written by Dr. John Poynet.</title>
            <author>Ridley, Nicholas, 1500?-1555.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 217 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57277</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R29319</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11076296</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11076296</idno>
            <idno type="VID">46245</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57277)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 46245)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1430:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief declaration of the Lords Supper with some other determinations and disputations concerning the same argument by the same author / written by Dr. Nicholas Ridley, Bishop of London during his imprisonment ; to which is annexed an extract of several passages to the same purpose out of a book intituled Diallacticon, written by Dr. John Poynet.</title>
                  <author>Ridley, Nicholas, 1500?-1555.</author>
                  <author>Ponet, John, 1516?-1556. Diallacticon viri boni et literati de veritate.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 68 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Chiswell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXVII [i.e. 1688]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A brief declaration of the Lords Supper" has separate t.p.: A breef declaration of the Lordes Supper / written by ... Nicholas Ridley. [London] : Printed at London, 1586, and reprinted for Ric. Chiswell, 1688.</note>
                  <note>"Diallacticon is in English and Latin in parallel columns."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF DECLARATION OF THE LORDS SUPPER WRITTEN BY BISHOP <hi>RIDLEY.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>Liber cui Titulus, <hi>[A Brief Declaration of the Lord's Supper,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Needham</hi> RR. in Chriſto P. ac D. D. <hi>Wilhelmo</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiep. <hi>Cant.</hi> a Sacr. Dom.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Junii</hi> 7. 1688.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BRIEF DECLARATION OF THE <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> WRITTEN By Dr. <hi>NICHOLAS RIDLEY,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>LONDON,</hi> During his IMPRISONMENT.</p>
            <p>With ſome other Determinations and Diſputations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſame Argument, by the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>To which is Annexed</p>
            <p>An Extract of ſeveral Paſſages to the ſame Purpoſe, out of a Book, Intituled, <hi>DIALLACTION,</hi> written by Dr. <hi>JOHN POYNET,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> in the Reigns of <hi>E.</hi> 6. and Q. <hi>Mary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> at the <hi>Roſe</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-yard,</hi> M DC LXXX VIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Doctrine of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> maintained by our Adverſaries of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> is ſo groſs, and highly repugnant to the firſt prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of reaſon, and univerſal ſenſe of mankind, that directly to defend it would be no leſs impoſſible than unſucceſsful. Artifices therefore were neceſſarily to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, which might palliate the deformity of ſo monſtrous an Opinion; and divert inquiſitive perſons from a direct ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination of it, by amuſing them with confident aſſertions and extraneous Controverſies. Among theſe, the difference of Opinion between the firſt Reformers and preſent Divines of the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath of late been propoſed and urged with the greateſt vehemency; as if the firſt Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers had believed ſomewhat equivalent to <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and our preſent Divines, by aſſerting no other than a figurative Preſence of the material Body of Chriſt, had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated from the belief of their Forefathers.</p>
            <p>We might juſtly admire the unreaſonable confidence of thoſe men, who are not aſhamed to propoſe ſo manifeſt and groſs a falſhood, and eſteem it the higheſt folly; if we did not remember that it is taken up to defend a deſperate Cauſe, which admits no better Remedies. Can any Man in his right wits believe that ſo many hundred Martyrs ſhould ſuffer death, and ſpend their blood for ſo inconſiderable a nicety, as was the difference between them and their Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors in the Doctrine of the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> if theſe late Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters may be believed? That both Parties ſhould diſpute
<pb facs="tcp:46245:4"/>
ſo earneſtly and vehemently againſt each other, and yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all agree in the main? That the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhops ſhould treat the Reformers as Hereticks for denying <hi>Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation;</hi> and the Reformers lay down their lives rather than acknowledge it; and yet neither the <hi>firſt</hi> to have defined it to be true, nor the <hi>laſt</hi> believed it to be falſe? Such crude Poſitions can find no entertainment, but in a mind already fitted to receive <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> it ſelf, that is, devoid of Senſe and Reaſon.</p>
            <p>If we enquire the Reaſons and Arguments, wherewith our Adverſaries maintain ſuch incredible and extravagant aſſertions, we ſhall find them to be no other than theſe, That the firſt Reformers taught and aſſerted a <hi>Real Preſence</hi> of the Body and Blood of Chriſt in the Sacrament; That they maintained the Body and Blood to be verily and indeed ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and received by the faithful Communicants; That they frequently affirmed the natural and ſubſtantial Body of Chriſt, that very Body which was taken by him of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> to be preſent in the Sacrament. Theſe very expreſſions are at this day uſed by the Divines of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> whom yet our Adverſaries pretend to have departed from the belief of their Forefathers in this matter: So that if they prove the <hi>firſt</hi> Reformers to have believed a material preſence of Chriſt's Body, they will prove our <hi>Preſent Divines</hi> to believe the ſame. For the whole Controverſy will come to this iſſue, Whether they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved any material Preſence of Chriſt's Body, or any part of it, either by converſion, ſubſtitution, or union? If they poſitively diſowned this, as moſt certainly they did; then whatſoever expreſſions they might uſe, they could believe no other than a figurative Preſence of Chriſt's Body properly ſo called; which our Adverſaries now traduce under the name of <hi>Zuinglianiſm.</hi> And, indeed, if we give them leave to explain themſelves, they tell us, That in ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb facs="tcp:46245:4"/>
they uſe the terms of <hi>Real Preſence, Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance,</hi> not as Philoſophers, but as Divines; and that by denying the Euchariſt to be a figure only, or a naked figure, they mean no more, than that it is a true and real commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication of the virtues and benefits of his Body, not only a meer figurative commemoration of them, which is the true notion of <hi>Zuinglianiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To prove this, and vindicate the honour of the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers and modern Divines of our Church, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the intire conformity of the belief of both; it is thought convenient to cauſe ſome one Treatiſe of the firſt Reformers concerning this Subject to be Reprinted, that ſo every one might judge for himſelf, whether the pretenſions of our Adverſaries be indeed true and juſt; or rather the Preſent is intirely conformable to the precedent Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> To this end, among all the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the firſt Reformers, this Treatiſe of Biſhop <hi>Ridley,</hi> which we here publiſh, will conduce moſt, by reaſon of the great and eminent Authority of the Author, which was ſo highly conſiderable beyond that of any other Reformer, that he may juſtly be eſteemed the Standard of the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> at that time. Not only the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of his great learning and eminent ſtation in the Church, renders this probable; but that great part which he had in managing the Affairs of the <hi>Reformation,</hi> and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary deference paid to his Authority, and truſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in him by all Convocations, and the whole body of the Reformers, demonſtrate it. None can reaſonably be put in competition with him, except Archbiſhop <hi>Cranmer;</hi> and he alſo in his diſputation at <hi>Oxford</hi> profeſſed, that he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his Opinion concerning the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> from Biſhop <hi>Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley.</hi> This the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy were ſo ſenſible of in the time of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> that by a plauſible calumny they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to perſuade the World, that the private opinion of
<pb facs="tcp:46245:5"/>
               <hi>Ridley</hi> was the only foundation of the Doctrine of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church of <hi>England:</hi> For <hi>Brooks</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fox</hi>'s Marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rol. <hi>Vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 425.</note> Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Commiſſioner, diſputing againſt him in the publick Schools at <hi>Oxford,</hi> uſed this among other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>What a weak and feeble ſtay in Religion is this, I pray you?</hi> Latimer <hi>leaneth to</hi> Cranmer, Cranmer <hi>to</hi> Ridley, <hi>and</hi> Ridley <hi>to the ſingularity of his own Wit: So that if you can overthrow the ſingularity of</hi> Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley<hi>'s Wit, then muſt needs the Religion of</hi> Cranmer <hi>and</hi> Latimer <hi>fall alſo.</hi> To which I may add the words of Dr. <hi>Fecknam,</hi> Abbot of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> in his Speech in Parliament, <hi>Primo Elizabethae,</hi> made in defence of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which I have ſeen in Manuſcript. <hi>Dr.</hi> Ridley, <hi>the notableſt learned of that Opinion in this Realm, did ſet forth at</hi> Paul<hi>'s Croſs the real preſence of Chriſt's Body in the Sacrament, with theſe words, which I heard, ſtaying then preſent; how that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil did believe the Sacrament of God was able to make of Stones Bread: And we Engliſh people, we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that Chriſt was the very Son of God, and yet will not believe that of Bread he made his very Body Fleſh and Blood; wherefore we are worſe than the Devil: ſince that our Saviour by expreſs words did more plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm the ſame, when at his laſt Supper he took Bread, and ſaid unto his Diſciples;</hi> Take ye, eat, this is my Body, which ſhall be given for you. <hi>And ſhortly after, the ſaid Mr. Doctor</hi> Ridley <hi>notwithſtanding this moſt plain and open Speech at</hi> Paul's Croſs, <hi>did deny the ſame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whether <hi>Fecknam</hi> hath truly repreſented the words of <hi>Ridley,</hi> is uncertain. But from the laſt words of this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage it is manifeſt, that ſome, even in that time, taking oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from this Sermon, had charged Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> with aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting a Material Preſence of Chriſt's Body in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb facs="tcp:46245:5"/>
and that he conſtantly denied himſelf to have meant or intended any ſuch preſence. In this therefore, and ſuch like expreſſions, he intended only (as himſelf aſſures us) to oppoſe thoſe, who <hi>ſo lightly eſteemed the Sacrament,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. vol.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 35.</note> 
               <hi>as to make of it but a figure. For that but maketh it a bare ſign, without any more profit.</hi> But to clear his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention in this matter from all remaining ſuſpicion of any kind of Material Preſence, I will annex a larger explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it in his own words, in his laſt examination before the Queens Commiſſioners, <hi>September</hi> 30. 1555.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In like ſort, as touching the Sermon, which I made at</hi> Pauls Croſs, <hi>you ſhall underſtand, that there were at</hi> Pauls, <hi>and divers other places, fixed railing Bills againſt the Sacrament, terming it Jack of the Box, the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Halter, Round Robbin, with ſuchlike un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly terms. For which cauſes, I, to rebuke the unreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend behaviour of certain evil diſpoſed perſons, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as reverendly of that Matter, as I might, declaring what eſtimation and reverence ought to be given to it; what danger enſued the miſ-handling thereof; affirming in that Sacrament to be truly and verily the Body and Blood of Chriſt, effectually by Grace and Spirit. Which words the unlearned underſtanding not, ſuppoſed that I had meant of the groſs and carnal being, which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Decrees ſet forth, That a Body having life and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhould be indeed under the ſhapes of Bread and Wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Treatiſe was written by Biſhop <hi>Ridley</hi> during his impriſonment, a little before his death, and ſeveral Copies of it diſperſed abroad; of which, ſome being carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond Sea, Dr. <hi>Grindall,</hi> and other Engliſh Exiles, concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a great deſire of cauſing it to be tranſlated into <hi>Latin,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid. p.</hi> 374.</note> and Printing it. The Biſhop hearing of this, deſired that by all means they would lay aſide their reſolution, till they
<pb facs="tcp:46245:6"/>
ſhould ſee how God would diſpoſe of him. Accordingly it was omitted till his death. Immediately after his Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom it was Tranſlated into elegant <hi>Latin,</hi> but in a Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſtical way, and Printed at <hi>Geneva</hi> 1556. in 12s. The Engliſh Copy was Printed at <hi>London</hi> 1586. 12s. which we have now cauſed to be faithfully Reprinted; adding to it out of Mr. <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Martyrology,</hi> divers Speeches, Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Determinations upon the ſame ſubject, which might farther illuſtrate and confirm his Opinion.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Becauſe the late Biſhop of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in his laſt Treatiſe, diſputing of the ancient Opinion of the Reformed Church of <hi>England</hi> concerning the Euchariſt, and as his Cauſe required it, maintaining the ſame aſſertion with our Adverſaries, That ſome material ſort of Preſence was then believed; doth mightily urge the Authority of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Poynet,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> at that time propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his <hi>Diallection;</hi> and becauſe that Book is not in Engliſh, I have ſelected and annexed ſeveral paſſages out of it, which may demonſtrate what was indeed his notion of the <hi>Real Preſence;</hi> That he denied all manner of Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Preſence, and perfectly agreeth with <hi>Ridley</hi> in explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature of it: And conſequently, that he is fouly either Miſrepreſented or Miſtaken by the Biſhop of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:6"/>
            <p>A BREEF DECLARATION OF THE <hi>Lordes Supper.</hi> WRITTEN By the ſinguler Learned Man, and moſte conſtant Martyr of Chriſte, <hi>NICHOLAS RIDLEY,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>LONDON,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Priſoner in <hi>Oxford,</hi> a little before he ſuffered Death for the true teſtimonye of JESUS CHRISTE.</p>
            <bibl>ROM. VIII.</bibl>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>For thy ſake are we killed all day long, and are counted as ſheep apoynted to be ſlain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neuertheleſſe, in all theſe thinges we ouercome through him that loue vs.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>LONDON,</hi> 1586. And Reprinted for <hi>Ric. Chiſwell,</hi> 1688.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:7"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>VNderſtand good (Reader) that this great Clark and bleſſed Martyr, Biſhop <hi>Nicholas Ridley,</hi> ſought not by ſettinge foorth any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table peece of learned woork, the vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the World, nor temporall freendſhip of men, for his preſent aduancement, much leſſe he hunted heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by for Biſhopricks and Benefices, as al his aduerſaries, the enemies of Chriſts Trueth and Ordinance com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly doo: but hauing conſideration of the great charge of Soules committed vnto him, and of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof, which the Iuſtice of God would require at his handes, intending therwithal to be found blam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les in the great daye of the Lord, ſeeing he was put a parte to defende the Goſpell: He not only forſook Landes, Goodes, World, Freends, and himſelfe with all, and teſtified the Trueth ſpecified in this Book by his learned mouth, in the open preſence of the World: but alſo to leaue a ſure Monument and Loue Token vnto his Flocke, hee hath regiſtred it by his owne Pen in this forme enſuinge, and ſealed it vp with his Blood. Foraſmuch then as he hath proued himſelfe no vain diſputer, no wethercocke, nor hipocrite, ſeeing hee
<pb facs="tcp:46245:8"/>
hath willinglye giuen his life for the Trueth, and in as much alſo as his loue and moſte conſtant chriſten Conſcience ſpeaketh vnto thee (gentle Reader) I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee for Chriſts ſake and thine owne, lend him thine indifferent hart and pacient hearing.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:8"/>
            <head>A BREEFE DECLARATION OF THE Lordes Supper.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>MANY</hi> things confounde a weake memory: A few places wel weighed and perceiued, lighten the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Trueth is there to be ſearched, where it is certain to be had, though God dooth ſpeake the trueth by man, yet in mans woord, which God hath not reuealed to be his, a man may doubt without miſtruſt in God. Chriſte is the trueth of God reuealed vnto man from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by God him ſelf, and therefore in his woord the trueth is to be founde, which is to be embraced of al that be his. Chriſt biddeth vs aſke, and we ſhall haue: ſearch and we ſhall finde: knocke, and it ſhall be opened unto vs. Therefore our Heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">The bleſſed Martirs praier.</note> Father, the Author and fountain of al trueth, the bottomles Sea of al vnderſtanding, ſend down we beſeech thée, thy holy ſpirit into our harts, and lighten our vnderſtanding with the beames of thy heauenly grace. We ask thée this, O mercifull Father, not in reſpect of our deſerts, but for thy déere Sonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſts ſake. Thou knoweſt, O heauenly Father, that the controuerſie about the Sacrament of the bleſſed body and blood of thy déer Sonne our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſte, hath troubled not of late onlye the Churche of <hi>England, Fraunce, Germanie,</hi> and <hi>Italye,</hi> but alſo many yéere agoe. The fault is ours (na dout) therfore, for we have deſerued thy plague. But (O Lord) be mercifull, and reléeue our miſerie with ſome lighte of grace. Thou knoweſt (O Lord) how this wicked world rolleth vp and down, and réeleth to and fro, and careth not what thy will is, ſo it may abide in wealth. If trueth haue wealthe, who are ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:46245:9"/>
ſtoute to defende the trueth, as they? But if Chriſtes croſſe be laid on trueths back, then they vaniſh away ſtraight, as Waxe before the fier. But theſe are not they, O Heauenly Father, for whome I make my moſte moane, but for thoſe ſilly ones, O Lord, which haue a zeale vnto thée: thoſe I mean, which wold <note place="margin">Note.</note> and wiſh to know thy wil, and yet are letted, holden backe, and blinded by the ſubtilties of Sathan and his miniſters, the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes of this wretched worlde, and the ſinfull luſts and affections of the fleſh. Alas Lord, thou knoweſt that we bée of our ſelues but fleſh, wherein there dwelleth nothing that is good. How then is it poſſible for man without thée (O Lord) to vnderſtand thy trueth indéed? Can the naturall man perceiue the wil of God? (O Lord) to whom thou giueſt a zeale of thée, giue them alſo (we beſeech thée) the knowledge of thy bleſſed wil. Suffer not them (O Lord) blindely to be led for to ſtriue againſt thée: as thou diddeſt thoſe (Alas) which crucified thine own Sonne, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue them (O Lord) for thy déere Sonnes ſake, for they know not what they doo. They doo think (Alas, O Lord) for lack of knowledge, that they doo vnto thée good ſeruice euen when againſt thée they doo moſte extremelye rage. Remember, O Lord, (we beſéech thee) for whome thy Martyr <hi>Stephen</hi> did praye, and whome thyne holy Apoſtle <hi>Paule</hi> did ſo truelye and earneſtlye loue: that for their ſaluation, hée wiſhed himſelf accurſed for them. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (O heauenly Father) the prayer of thy déere Sonne, our Sauiour Chriſte vpon the croſſe, when be ſaide vnto thée, <hi>O Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther forgiue them, they know not what they doo.</hi> With this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes, O good Lord, giue me, I beſéech thée, thy grace, ſo héer bréefly to ſet foorth the ſayings of thy Sonne our Sauiour Chriſte, and of his Euangeliſtes, and of his Apoſtles, that in this aforeſaid controuerſie, the lighte of the trueth, by the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of thy woord, may ſhine vnto all them that loue thée.</p>
            <p>Of the Lords laſt ſupper doo ſpeak expreſlye the Euangeliſts, <hi>Mathew, Mark,</hi> and <hi>Luke:</hi> but none more plainelye nor more fully declareth the ſame, then dooth S. <hi>Paule,</hi> partely in the tenth Chapter, but ſpecially in the xj. chapter of his firſt epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians.</hi> As <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> doo agrée much in woordes, ſo doo likewiſe <hi>Luke</hi> and S. <hi>Paule.</hi> But all iiij. no doubte, as they were all taught in one ſchoole, and inſpired with one ſpirit, ſo taught they as one trueth. God grant vs to vnderſtande it wel. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mathew</hi> ſetteth foorth Chriſtes Supper thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When euen was come, he ſat down with the xij. &amp;c. As they did eat, Jeſus took bread and gave thankes, brake it, and gave it to the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>and ſaide: Take, eat: this is my body. And he took the cup</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:46245:9"/>
               <hi>and gaue thankes, gaue it to them, ſaying, Drink ye al of this: for this is my blood of the newe teſtament that is ſhed for many for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes, I ſay vnto you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the vine tree, untill that daye, when I ſhall drink that newe in my fathers kingdome. And when they had ſayed grace they went out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Mark</hi> ſpeaketh it thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And as they eate, Jeſus took bread, bleſſed, and brake, and gaue to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>them and ſaied, take, eat, this is my body. And took the cup gaue thankes, and gaue it to them, and they all drank of it. And he ſaid vnto them: This is my bloud of the new teſtament, which is ſhed for many. Verily I ſaye vnto you, I wil drink no more of the fruit of the vine, vntill that day, that I drink that newe, in the kingdome of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Héere <hi>Mathew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> doo agree not only in the matter, but alſo almoſte fully in the forme of woords. In <hi>Mathew,</hi> gaue thankes. <hi>Mark</hi> hath one woorde, Bleſſed: which ſignifieth in this place al one. And where <hi>Mathew</hi> ſaith, <hi>Drink ye al of this, Mark</hi> ſaith, <hi>they al drank of it.</hi> And where <hi>Mathew</hi> ſaithe, <hi>of this fruit of the vine; Mark</hi> leaueth out the woord <hi>this,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>of the fruit of the vine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us ſee likewiſe, what agréement (in forme of woords) is betwéene S. <hi>Luke</hi> and S. <hi>Paule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luke</hi> writeth thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He took bread, gaue thankes, brake it and gaue it to them, ſaying;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>this is my body which is giuen for you, this doo in remembrance of me. Likewiſe alſo when they had ſupped, he took the Cup, ſaying, this Cup is the newe Teſtament in my bloud, which is ſhedde for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſetteth foorth the Lords Supper thus,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord Ieſus, the ſame night, in the which he was betraied, took</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>Bread, and gaue thankes and brake, and ſaide, take, eate, this is my body which is broken for you. This doo in remembrance of me. After the ſame maner he took the Cup, when ſupper was doon, ſaying, this Cup is the new teſtament in my bloud. This doo as often as yee ſhall drink it in remembrance of me. For as often as ye ſhall eate this breade, and drinke this cup, ye ſhall ſhewe the Lords deathe, vntill he come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Héere where S. <hi>Luke</hi> ſaith, which is <hi>given; Paule</hi> ſaith, which is <hi>broken.</hi> And as <hi>Luke</hi> addeth to the woordes of <hi>Paule</hi> ſpoken of the Cup which is ſhed for you, ſo likewiſe <hi>Paule</hi> addeth to the woords thereof, <hi>this doo, as often as yee ſhall drinke it, in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</hi> The reſt that followeth in S. <hi>Paule,</hi> both there and in the tenth Chapter, perteineth unto the right vſe of the Lords Supper.</p>
            <p>Thus the Euangeliſtes and S. <hi>Paule</hi> haue rehearſed the woords and woorke of Chriſte, whereby he did inſtitute and ordaine this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:46245:10"/>
holy Sacrament of his bodye and blood to be a perpetuall remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance vnto his comming againe of him ſelfe, I ſay that is of his body giuen for vs, and of his blood ſhed for the remiſſion of ſinnes. But this remembrance which to thus ordained, as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thereof is Chriſte, bothe God and Man, ſo by the almightye power of God, if far paſſeth al kindes of remembrances, that any other man is able to make either of him ſelfe, or of any other thinge. For whoſoever receiueth this holy Sacrament thus or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deined in remembrance of Chriſte, he receiueth therwith either death or life. In this (I truſt) we doo al agrée, For S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith of the godly receiuers in the tenth Chapter of his firſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle vnto the <hi>Cerinthians, The Cup of bleſſinge, which we bleſſe, is it not the pertaking or felowſhip of Chriſtes bloud?</hi> And alſo ſaithe, <hi>the Breade which wee break</hi> (and meaneth at the Lords Lable) <hi>Is it not the partaking or felowſhip of Chriſts body?</hi> Now the partaking of Chriſtes body and of his blood vnto the faithfull and godly, is the partaking or felowſhip of life and immortalitie. And againe of the bad and vngodly receiuers, S. <hi>Paule</hi> as plainly ſaith thus. <hi>He that eateth of this bread, and drinketh of this cup vnworthily, is gilty of the body and bloud of the Lord.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Note.</note>
            </p>
            <p>O how neceſſary then it is, if we loue life, and would eſchue deathe, to trye and examine our ſelues, before we eate of this bread, and drink of this cup, for els aſſuredly, he that eateth and drinketh thereof vnworthilye, eateth and drinketh his own damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe he eſtéemeth not the Lords body, that is, he reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enceth not the Lordes bodye with the honour that is due vnto him.</p>
            <p>And that which was ſaide, that with the receite of the holye Sacrament of the bleſſed body and bloud of Chriſte is receiued of every one, good and bad, either life or death: it is not ment, that they whiche are dead before God, may heerby receiue life: or the liuinge before God, can heerby receiue death.</p>
            <p>For as none is meete to receiue naturall food, wherby the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral life is nouriſhed, except he be borne and liue before: ſo no man can feed (by the receit of this holy Sacrament) of the food of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, except he be regenerated and borne of God before. And on the other ſide, no man heer receiueth damnation whiche is not dead before. Thus hethertoo without al doubt, God is my witneſſe I ſaye ſo far as I doo knowe, there is no controuerſie amonge them that be learned, in the Churche of <hi>England</hi> (concerninge the matter of this Sacrament) but al doo agree, whether they be new or olde, and to ſpeak plain, and as ſome of them doo odiouſly cal either other, whether they be Proteſtantes, Papiſts, Phariſies or Goſpellers. And as all doo agree hithertoo, in the aforeſaid Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:46245:10"/>
ſo all doo deteſte, abborre and condemne the wicked he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie of the <hi>Meſſalonians</hi> which otherwiſe be called <hi>Eutichets,</hi> which ſaide that the holy Sacrament can neither doo no good nor harme. All do alſo condemne thoſe wicked Anabaptiſtes, which put no difference between the Lords Table and the Lords meat, and their owne. And becauſe charity would, that we ſhould, (if it be poſſible, and ſo far as we may with the ſauegarde of good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and maintenance of the trueth) agree with all men: therfore me thinkes it is not charitablye doon to burthen any man (either newe or olde, as they call them) further, then ſuch doo declare themſelues, to diſſent from that we are perſwaded to be trueth, or pretend thertoo to be controuerſies, where as none ſuch are in deed: and ſo to multiply the debate, the which the more it doth increaſe, the further it doth depart from the vnitie, that the true Chriſtian ſhould deſire.</p>
            <p>And again this is true, that trueth nother needeth nor wil be <note place="margin">What it is to lye. The ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous lyes of the Papiſts.</note> maintained with lies. It is alſo a true prouerb, <hi>That it is euen ſinne to lye vpon the Deuil.</hi> For though by thy lye thou dooſt neuer ſo much ſpeak againſt the Deuil, yet in that thou lieſt in deed thou woorkeſt the Deuils woorke, thou dooſt him ſeruice, and takeſt the Deuils part. Now whether then they doo godlye and chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tablye, which either by their Pen in Writing, or by their Woordes in Preaching, doo beare the ſimple people in hand, that thoſe which thus doo teach and beleue, doo go about to make the holye Sacrament (ordeined by Chriſte himſelfe) a thing no better then a peece of common Bread: or that doo ſaye, that ſuch doo make the holye Sacrament of the bleſſed bodye and blood of Chriſte, nothing els but a bare ſigne or a figure, to repreſent Chriſte none otherwiſe, then the Ivye buſhe doth repreſent the Wine in a Tauern, or as a vile perſon gorgiouſlye apparalled, maye repreſent a King or a Prince in a playe. Alas let men leaue lying, and ſpeak trueth everye one, not only to his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: but alſo of his neighboure, for wee are members one of an other ſaith Saint <hi>Paule.</hi> The controuerſie (no doubt) which at this daye troubleth the Church (wherin any mean learned man, either olde or newe, dooth ſtand in) is not, whether the holy Sacrament of the body and blood of Chriſte, is no better then a peece of common breade or no: or whether the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is no more to be regarded, then the Table of any earthly man or no: or whether it is but a bare ſigne or figure of Chriſte and nothing elſe or no. For all do graunt, that S. <hi>Paules</hi> woordes doo require, that the bread which we break, is the partaking of the body of Chriſte, and alſo doo graunte him that eateth of that bread, or drinketh of that cup vnwoorthely, to be gilty of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:46245:11"/>
Lords death, and to eate and drinke his owne damnation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe be eſteemeth not the Lords body. All doo graunt, that theſe woords of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> (when he ſaith: <hi>If we eate. it aduanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth vs nothing: or if wee eate not, wee want nothing therby)</hi> are not ſpoken of the Lords Table, but of other common meats.</p>
            <p>Thus then betherto yet, we all agree. But now let vs ſee, <note place="margin">Wherin the controuerfie conſiſteth.</note> wherin the diſſention doth ſtand. The vnderſtanding of it, wherin it cheeflye ſtandeth, is a ſtep to the true ſearching foorthe of the trueth. For who can ſeeke well a remedye, if he knowe not before the diſeaſe? It is neither to be denied nor diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled, that in the matter of this Sacrament there be diuers poyntes, wherin men (counted to be learned) cannot agree. As, whether there be any Tranſubſtantiation of the bread, or no: any corporall and carnall preſence of Chriſtes ſubſtance, or no. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adoration (due only vnto God) is to be doon vnto the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or no? and whether Chriſtes bodye be there offered in deed vnto the heauenly Father, by the Preeſte or no? and whether the euill man receiueth the naturall body of Chriſte or no. Yet neuertheles as in a man diſeaſed in diuers partes, commonly the originall cauſe of ſuch diuers diſeaſes which is ſpred abroad in the body, doo come from one cheefe member, as from the ſtomacke, or from the head, euen ſo all fiue aforeſaid doo chiefly hange vpon this one queſtion, which is, <hi>What is the matter of the Sacrament?</hi> whether is it the naturall ſubſtance of bread, or the naturall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſts owne body? The trueth of this queſtion truelye tried out and agreed vpon, no doubt ſhall ceaſe the controuerſie in all the reſt. For if it be Chriſtes owne natural body, born of the Virgin: then aſſuredlye (ſeeing that all learned men in <hi>England</hi> ſo far as I knowe, bothe newe and olde, graunt there to be but one ſubſtance, then I ſay, they muſt needs graunt Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation: that is, a change of the ſubſtance of breade, into the ſubſtance of Chriſtes bodye. Then alſo they muſt needs graunt the carnal and corporal preſence of Chriſtes body. Then muſt the Sacrament be adorred with the honour due to Chriſte him ſelfe, for the vnitie of the two natures in one perſon. Then if the Preeſt do offer the Sacrament, he dooth offer indeed Chriſte him ſelf. And finally the murtherer, the aduouterer, or wicked man receiuinge the Sacrament, muſte needes then receiue alſo the naturall ſubſtance of Chriſtes owne bleſſed bodye, bothe fleſhe and blood.</p>
            <p>Now on the other ſide, if after the trueth ſhal be truely tried out, it ſhall be found, that the ſubſtance of breade is the naturall ſubſtance of the Sacrament, although for the change of the vſe, office and dignitie of the bread, the bread indeed Sacramentally
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:46245:11"/>
is changed into the bodye of Chriſte, as the water in Baptiſme is ſacramentally changed into the fountaine of regeneration, and yet the natural ſubſtance therof remaineth al one, as was before: if I ſaye the true ſolucion of that former queſtion (wherupon all theſe controuerſies doo hang) be, that the natural ſubſtance of bread, is the materiall ſubſtance in the Sacrament of Chriſtes bleſſed body: then muſt it needes followe of the former propoſition (confeſſed of al that be named to be learned, ſo far as I doo knowe, in <hi>England)</hi> whiche is that there is but one materiall ſubſtance in the Sacrament of the body, and one only likewiſe in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the blood, that there is no ſuch thinge indeede and in truethe, as they call Tranſubſtantiation: for the ſubſtance of bread remaineth ſtil in the Sacrament of the body, then alſo the naturall ſubſtance of Chriſtes humain nature, which he took of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is in Heauen, where it reigneth now in glory, and not heer incloſed vnder the forme of bread, then the godly honour, which is onely due vnto God the creator, may not be doon vnto the creature without idolatrye and ſacrilege, is not to be doon vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holye Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Then alſo the wicked, I mean the impenitent murtherrer, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uluterer, or ſuche like, doo not receiue the naturall ſubſtance of the bleſſed body and blood of Chriſte. Finally, then dooth it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, that Chriſtes bleſſed body and blood, which was once onlye offered and ſhed vpon the Croſſe, beinge auaylable for the ſinnes of all the whole world, is offered vp no more, in the naturall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance therof, nother by the Preeſt, nor any other thing. But heer before wee go any further to ſearch in this matter, and to wade (as it were) to ſearch and trye out (as we may) the trueth heerof in the Scripture, it ſhall doo well by the way to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that thus make anſwere and ſolucione vnto the former principall queſtion, doo take away ſimply and abſolutely the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſtes bodye and blood, from the Sacrament ordeined by Chriſte, and dulye miniſtred according to his holy ordinance and inſtitution of the ſame. Vndoubtedly they doo deny that btterlye, either ſo to ſaye, or ſo to meane. Heerof if any man doo or will doubt, the bookes which are written already in this matter of them, that thus doo anſwere, will make the matter plaine.</p>
            <p>Now then will you ſaye, what kinde of preſence doo they graunt, and what doo they denye? Breeflye they deny the preſence of Chriſts body in the naturall ſubſtance of his humain and aſſumpt nature, and graunt the preſence of the ſame by grace: that is, they affirme and ſaye, that the ſubſtance of the naturall bodye and blood of Chriſte is only remaining in Heaven, and ſo ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:46245:12"/>
be vnto the latter daye, when he ſhall come againe in glorye, (accompanied with the Angels of Heauen) to iudge both the quicke and the deade. And that the ſame natural ſubſtance of the very body and blood of Chriſte, becauſe it is vnited vnto the deuine nature in Chriſte the ſecond perſon of the Trinitle. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it hath not onely life in it ſelfe, but is alſo able to giue and dooth giue life vnto ſo many as be or ſhal be partakers therof, that is, that to all that doo beleeue on his name, which are not borne of blood (as S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith) or of the wil of the fleſhe, or of the will of man, but are borne of God: though the ſelf-ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance abide ſtill in Heauen, and they for the time of their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage dwel heer vpon Earth: by grace I ſay, that is, by the life mencioned in <hi>Iohn</hi> and the properties of the ſame, meete for our pilgrimage heer upon earth, the ſame body of Chriſte is heere preſent with vs. Euen as for example, wee ſaye, the ſame Sunne (which in ſubſtance) neuer remoueth his place out of the Heauens, is yet preſent heer by his beams, light and naturall influence, where it ſhineth vpon the earth. For Gods Woord and his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments be (as it were the beams of Chriſt) which is <hi>Sol iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> the Sunne of righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Thus haſt thou heard, of what ſort or ſect ſoeuer thou be, wherin dooth ſtand the principall ſtate and cheef poynte of all the controuerſies, which doo properly pertain vnto the nature of this Sacrament. As for the vſe therof I graunt there be many other thinges, wherof heer I haue ſpoken nothing at all. And nowe leaſte thou iuſtely mighteſt complain, and ſay, that I haue in openinge of this matter doon nothing els, but digged a pitte, and haue not ſhut it vp again: or broken a gap, and haue not made it vp again: or opened the booke, and haue not clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it again: or els to call me what thou liſteſt, as neuterall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler, or what ſoeuer els thy luſt and learning ſhall ſerue thee to name me woorſſe: Therfore heer now I wil (by Gods grace) not only ſhortly, but ſo cleerely and plainly as I can make thee to knowe, whether of the aforeſaid two anſwers to the former prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall ſtate and cheef poynt dooth like me beſt: yea and alſo I will holde all thoſe accurſed, whiche in this matter that now ſo troubleth the Church of Chriſt haue of God receiued the kepe of knowledge, and yet go about to ſhut up the doores ſo that they themſelues will not enter in nor ſuffer other that woulde. And as for mine owne parte, I conſider but of late what charge and cure of ſoule hath bin committed vnto me, wherof God knoweth, how ſoon I ſhal be called to giue accounte: and alſo now in this worlde what perill and danger of the lawes concerning my life I am now in at this preſent time. What folly were it then for me,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:46245:12"/>
now to diſſemble with God, of whom aſſuredly I looke and hope by Chriſte to haue euerlaſting life? Seing that ſuch charge and danger bothe before God and man, doo compaſſe mee in round about on euery ſide: therfore God willing I will frankly and freelye vtter my minde, and thoughe my bodye be captiue, yet my tung and my pen as long as I may ſhall frely ſet forth, that which vndubtedlye I am perſwaded to be the trueth of Godes Woorde. And yet I will do it vnder this proteſtation, call me Proteſtant who luſteth, I paſſe not therof. My proteſtation ſhall be thus: that my minde is and euer ſhal be (God willinge) to ſet foorth ſincerelye the true ſence and meaninge (to the beſte of my vnderſtanding) of Godes moſt holy woorde, and not to decline from the ſame, either for feare of worldly danger, or els for hope of gaine.</p>
            <p>I doo proteſte alſo due obedience &amp; ſubmiſſion of my iudgemente in this my writing, and in all other mine affairs vnto thoſe of Chriſts Church, which be truly learned in Gods holy Woord, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in Chriſts Name and guided by his Spirit. After this proteſtation, I doo plainely affirme and ſay, that the ſecond <note place="margin">Anſwere to the cheef que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion.</note> queſtion and principall poynt, I am perſwaded to be the very true meaning and ſence of Gods holy Woord: that is, that the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſubſtance of bread and wine is the true materiall ſubſtance of the holy Sacrament of the bleſſed body and blood of our Sauiour Chriſte: and the places of Scripture wherupon this my faith is grounded, be theſe, both concerning the Sacrament of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and alſo the bloud.</p>
            <p>Firſte let vs repete the beginninge of the inſtitution of the Lords Supper wherin all the three Euangeliſts, and S. <hi>Paule</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt in woords doo agree, ſaying that <hi>Ieſus took bread, gaue thanks, brake, and gaue it to the Diſciples ſayinge: Take, eate, this is my bodye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heer it appeareth plainly, that Chriſte calleth very bread his body. For that which he took, was very bread. In this all men doo agree. And that which he took, after he had giuen thankes, he brake: and that which he took and brake, he gaue to his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: and that which be took, brake, and gaue to his Diſciples he ſaide him ſelfe of it: <hi>This is my body.</hi> So it appeareth plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye that Chriſt called very bread his body. But very bread canot be his bodye in very ſubſtance therof: therfore it muſt needs haue an other meaninge. Which meaninge appeareth plainelye what it is, by the next ſentence that followeth immediatly, both in <hi>Luke</hi> and in <hi>Paule.</hi> And that is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doo this in remembrance of me.</hi> Wher-vpon it ſeemeth vnto me to be euident, that Chriſte did take bread, and called it his bodye, for that he would therby inſtitute a perpetuall remembrance of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:46245:13"/>
his body: ſpeciallye of the ſinguler benefite of our redemtion, which he would then procure and purchaſe vnto vs by his bodye vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſſe. But bread retaining ſtill his owne very naturall ſubſtance, may be thus by grace, (and in a ſacramental ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) his body: wheras els the very bread which he took, brake, and gaue them, could not be any wiſe his naturall bodye. For that were confuſion of ſubſtances, and therfore the very woordes of Chriſte ioynes with the next ſentence following, both enforceth vs to confeſſe the verye bread, to remaine ſtill, and alſo openeth vnto vs, how that bread maye be and is thus by his deuine power his body, which was giuen for vs. But heere I remember I haue red in ſome writers of the contrarye opinion, which Chriſte did take, be brake. For ſay they, after his taking, he bleſſed it as <hi>Mark</hi> dooth ſpeak. And by his bleſſing, be changed the natural ſubſtance of the bread into the natural ſubſtance of his body: and ſo although he took the bread, and bleſſed it, yet becauſe in bleſſing he changed the ſubſtance of it, he brake not the breade, which then was not there, but only the forme therof.</p>
            <p>Vnto this obiection I haue two plain anſwers, both grounded vpon Gods woord. The one I will heer rehearſe, the other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer I will differ, vntil I ſpeak of the Sacrament of the blood. Mine anſwere heer is taken out of the plaine woords of S. <hi>Paule</hi> which dooth manifeſtly confound this fantaſtical inuention, firſt inuented (I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een) of Pope <hi>Innocentius,</hi> and after confirmed by the ſubtile ſophiſter <hi>Duns,</hi> and lately renewed now in our daies, with an eloquent ſtile and much fineneſſe of wit. But what can crafty inuention, ſubtiltye in ſophiſmes, eloquence or fineneſſe of wit <note place="margin">Mar. Antho. Conſtan. Gardenar.</note> preuaile againſt the vnfallible Woorde of God? What neede we to ſtriue and contend what thinge we break, for <hi>Paule</hi> ſaieth, ſpeaking vndoubtedly of the Lords Table: <hi>The bread</hi> (ſaieth he) <hi>which we break, is it not the partaking or felowſhip of the Lords body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherupon it followeth, that after the thanks giving it is bread which we break. And how often in the <hi>Acts of the Apoſtles</hi> is the Lords Supper ſignified by breaking of bread? <hi>They did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Luke) in the Apoſtles Doctrine, Communion, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>breaking of bread. And they brake breade in euery houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And again in an other place when they were come together to breake bread, &amp;c. S. <hi>Paule</hi> which ſetteth foorth moſte fully in his writinge both the doctrine and the right vſe of the Lords Supper, and the Sacramentall eating and drinkinge of Chriſts body and blood, calleth it fiue times bread, bread, bread, bread, bread.</p>
            <p>The ſacramentall bread is the miſticall body, and ſo it is called <note place="margin">The ſecond reaſon.</note> in Scripture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. as it is called the naturall body of Chriſte.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:46245:13"/>
But Chriſts miſticall body is the congregation of Chriſtians. Now no man was euer ſo fond, as to ſay, that that ſacramentall breade is tranſubſtantiated and changed into the ſubſtance of the congregatione. Wherfore no man ſhoulde likewiſe think, or ſaye, that the breade is tranſubſtantiated and changed into the naturall ſubſtance of Chriſtes humaine nature.</p>
            <p>But my minde is not héere to write what may be gathered out of Scriptures for this purpoſe, but onely to note heer breefly, thoſe which ſeem vnto me, to be the moſt plaine places. Therfore contented to haue ſpoken thus muche of the Sacramentall bread: I will nowe ſpeake a little of the Lords cup.</p>
            <p>And this ſhall be my third Argument grounded vpon Chriſtes <note place="margin">The third Argument.</note> owne woordes. The natural ſubſtance of the ſacramentall Wine remaineth ſtill, and is the material ſubſtance of the Sacrament of the blood of Chriſte: Therfore it is likewiſe ſo in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Bread.</p>
            <p>I know that he that is of a contrarye opinion, will denye the former parte of mine Argument. But I will prooue it thus by the plaine woords of Chriſte himſelfe, both in <hi>Mathewe</hi> and in <hi>Marke.</hi> Chriſtes woordes are theſe: after the wordes ſaide vpon the cup: <hi>I ſaye vnto you,</hi> ſaith Chriſte, <hi>I will not drinke hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorthe of this fruite of the vine tree, vntill I ſhall drink that new in my fathers kingdome.</hi> Heere note how Chriſte calleth plainly his cup the fruit of the vine tree. But the fruit of the vine is very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral wine. Wherfore the naturall ſubſtance of the wine doothe remaine ſtill in the Sacrament of Chriſtes Blood.</p>
            <p>And heer in ſpeaking of the Lords Cup: it commeth vnto my remembrance the vanitie of <hi>Innocentius</hi> his fantaſticall inuention, which by <hi>Paules</hi> woordes I did confute before, and héer did promiſe ſomwhat more to ſpeake, and that is this: if this Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiatione be made by this woorde, Bleſſed, in <hi>Mark</hi> ſaid vpon the breade, as <hi>Innocentius</hi> that Pope did ſaye: then ſurely ſeeing that woord is not ſaide of Chriſte neither in any of the Euangeliſtes nor in S. <hi>Paule</hi> vpon the cup: There is no Tranſubſtantiatione of the Wine at all. For where the cauſe dooth falle, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not follow the effect. But the ſacramental Bread and the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Wine doo both remain in their naturall ſubſtance a like, and if the one be not changed, as of the ſacramental Wine it appeareth euidently: then there is no ſuch Tranſubſtantiatione in nother of them both.</p>
            <p>All that truſt and affirme this change of the ſubſtance of breade <note place="margin">The Papiſts, affirme they wot not what.</note> and mine into the ſubſtance of Chriſtes Bodye and Blood called Tranſubſtantiation: doo alſo ſay this change to be made by a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine forme of preſcripte woordes, and none other. But what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:46245:14"/>
they be that make the change, either of the one, or of the other: vndoubtedlye euen they that doo write moſte finelye in theſe our daies, almoſt confeſſe plainely, that they can not tel. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoughe they graunt to certaine of the olde authors, as <hi>Chriſoſtom,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe:</hi> that theſe woords <hi>This is my body,</hi> are the woords of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardener to the</hi> 48. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection.</hi>
               </note> of the Sacrament of the bodye: yet ſay they, theſe woords may wel be ſo called, becauſe they doo aſſure vs of the couſecration therof, whether it be doon before theſe woords be ſpoken or no.</p>
            <p>But as for this their doubte, concerning the Sacrament of the bodye, I let it paſſe. Let vs now conſider the woords which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Cup. This is firſt euident, that as <hi>Mathewe</hi> much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeeth with <hi>Mark,</hi> and likewiſe <hi>Luke</hi> with <hi>Paule</hi> muche agréeeth béerein in forme of woordes, ſo in the ſame forme of woordes in <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> is diuers from that which is in <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paule:</hi> the olde authors doo moſte rehearſe the forme of woordes in <hi>Mathewe</hi> and <hi>Marke:</hi> becauſe I wéene they ſéemed to them moſte cléere. But béer I woulde knowe, whether it is credibly or no, that <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> when they celebrated the Lordes Supper with their congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, that they did not not vſe the ſame forme of woords (at the Lords Table) which they wrote, <hi>Luke</hi> in his Goſpell, and <hi>Paule</hi> in his Epiſtle. Of <hi>Luke,</hi> becauſe he was a Phiſition, whether ſome will graunt, that he might be a Préeſſe or no, and was able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the order of préeſthood, which (they ſay) is giuen by the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of theſe woordes ſaide by the Biſhop: <hi>Take thou authoritye to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the quick and the deade.</hi> I can not tell, but if they ſhoulde be ſo ſtraight vpon <hi>Luke</hi> either for his crafte, or eis for lack of ſuche <note place="margin">Peter and Paule had no ſuch preeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood as the Papiſts haue.</note> power giuen him by vertue of the aforeſaid woords: then I wéene, both <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> are in danger to be depoſed of their préeſthood, for the craft either of Fiſhinge, which was <hi>Peters:</hi> or making of Tentes, which was <hi>Paules,</hi> were more vile, then the ſcience of Phiſicke.</p>
            <p>And as for thoſe ſacramentall woords of the order of Préeſthood, to haue authoritie to ſacrifice both for the quicke and the deade, I wéene <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> (if they were both a liue) were not able to prooue, that euer Chriſte gaue them ſuch authoritie, or euer ſaid any ſuch woordes vnto them. But I will let <hi>Luke</hi> goe, and becauſe <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh more for him ſelfe: I will rehearſe his woords: <hi>That (ſaith Paule) whiche I receiued of the Lord, I gaue vnto you. For the Lorde Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo he ſetteth foorth the whole inſtitution and right vſe of the Lordes Supper. Now ſéeing that S. <hi>Paule</hi> heer ſaith, that whiche he receiued of the Lord, he had giuen them, and that whiche he hath receiued and giuen them before by woord of mouth: now he rehearſeth and writeth the ſame in his Epiſtle, is it crediblye that <hi>Paule</hi> woulde neuer vſe this forme of woords, vpon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:46245:14"/>
the Lords cop, which (as he ſaith) he receaued of the Lord, that he had giuen them before, and now rehearſeth in his Epiſtle? I <hi>truſt</hi> no man is far from al reaſon, but he wil graunt me, that this is not likely ſo to be.</p>
            <p>Now then, if you graunt mee, that <hi>Paule</hi> did vſe the forme of woords, which he writeth: Let vs then rehearſe and conſider <hi>Paules</hi> woorde, which he ſaith, Chriſt ſpake thus vpon the Cuppe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament in my blood, this doo: as often as ye ſhall drinke it in the remembrance of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Héer I woulde knowe, whether that Chriſts woords ſpoken vpon the cup were not as mighty in woork, and as effectuall in ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to all intentes, conſtrictions, and <hi>purpoſes,</hi> (as all our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men doo ſpeak) as they were ſpoken vpon the breade. If this be graunted, which thinge I think no man can deny: then fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I reaſon thus. But the woorde <hi>(Is)</hi> in the woords ſpoken vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords breade dooth mightely ſignifie (ſay they) the change of the ſubſtance of that which goeth before it into the ſubſtance of that which followeth after, that is, of the ſubſtance of bread into the ſubſtance of Chriſtes bodye, when Chriſte ſaith: <hi>This is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi> Now then if Chriſts woords which are ſpoken vpon the cup, which <hi>Paule</hi> heere rehearſeth be of the ſame might and power, both in woorking and ſignifying: then muſt this woord <hi>(Is)</hi> when Chriſte ſaithe: <hi>This Cup is the new Teſtament, &amp;c.</hi> turne the ſubſtance of the cup into the ſubſtance of the new teſtament. And if thou wilt ſaye, that this woorde <hi>(Is)</hi> nother maketh nor ſignifieth any ſuch change of the cup, Although it be ſaid of Chriſte, that this cup is the new teſtament, yet Chriſt ment no ſuch change as that. Marry ſir, euen ſo ſaye I, when Chriſte ſaid of the bread, which hée took, and after thanks giuen, brake, and gaue them, ſaying: <hi>Take, eat, this is my body,</hi> he ment no more any ſuch change of the ſubſtance of breade into the ſubſtance of his naturall body, then he ment of the change and tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtamiation of the cup into the ſubſtance of the newe Tellament. And if thou wilt ſaye that the woord <hi>(Cup)</hi> héer in Chriſts woords dooth not ſignifie the Cup it ſelf, but the Wine or thing centeined in the cup, by a figure called <hi>Metonymia,</hi> for that Chriſts <note place="margin">Note well the Papiſts errour conſuted.</note> woordes ſo ment, and muſte néeds be taken: thou ſaiſt very wel. But I pray thée by the way, héer note two things, Firſt that this woorde, <hi>Is,</hi> hath no ſuche ſtrength or ſignification in the Lordes woords, to make or to ſignifie any tranſubſtanciation. Secondly, that the Lords woords wherby he inſtituted the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of his blood: he vſeth a figuratiue ſpeach. How vaine then is it, that ſome ſo earneſtly doo ſay, as it were an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible rule, that in doctrine and in the inſtitution of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Chriſte vſed no figurs, but all his woordes are to be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:46245:15"/>
ſtrained to their proper ſignifications: when as héer what ſoeuer thou ſaieſt was in the cup, nother that nor the cup it ſelf, taking eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye woorde in his proper ſignification, was the new teſtament, but in vnderſtanding that which was in the cup by the cup that is a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue ſpeache: yea and alſo thou canſt not verifie or truly ſay of that whether thou ſaieſt it was wine or Chriſts bloud, to be the new teſtament without a figure alſo. Thus in one ſentence ſpoken of Chriſte, in the inſtitution of the Sacrament of his bloud, the figure muſt help vs twiſe. So vntrue it is, that ſome doo write, that Chriſte vſeth no figure in the doctrine of faith, nor in the inſtitution of his ſacraments. But ſome ſay, if we ſhall thus admit figures in doctrine: then ſhall all the articles of our faith, by figures and allegories ſhortly be transformed and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſed. I ſay it is like fault, and euen the ſame, to denye the figure, where the place ſo reguirethe to be underſtanded, as bainly to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de doc. Chriſtiana. li.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 16.</note> make it a figuratiue ſpeach, which is to be vnderſtanded in his proper ſignification.</p>
            <p>The rules wherby the ſpeech is knowen, when it is figuratiue, &amp; wherby it is none. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in his booke. <hi>De doctrina Chriſtiana,</hi> giueth diuers learned leſſons, very neceſſary to be knowen of the ſtudents in Gods woorde. Of the which, oue I wil rehearſe, which is this: <hi>If</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the ſcripture dooth ſeeme to commaund a thing, which is wicked or vngodly, or to forbid a thing that charitie doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: then know,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the ſpeach is figuratiue.</hi> And for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, he bringethe the ſaying of Chriſte, in the vj. chapter of S. <hi>Iohn. Except ye eate of the fleſhe of the ſonne of man, and drinke his blood:</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardiner in his anſwers to the</hi> 161. &amp; 226. <hi>obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Note.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ye can not haue life in you. It ſeemeth to commaund a wicked or anvngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thing, wherfore it is a figuratiue ſpeech, commaunding to haue Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and felowſhip with Chriſts paſſion, and deuoutly and holſomly to lay vp in memory, that his fleſh was crucified and wounded for vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And héer I can not but maruail at ſome men, ſurely of much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent fineneſſe of wit, and of great eloquence, that are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to write and ſaye, that this aforeſaide ſaying of Chriſte is after S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> a figuratiue ſpeache indéede: howbeit not vnto the learned, but to the vnlearned. Héere let any man that but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently vnderſtandeth the <hi>Latin</hi> tongue, reade the place in S. <hi>Auſtine:</hi> and if ye perceiue not cléerly S. <hi>Auguſtins</hi> woords, and mine to be contrarye, let me abide therof the rebuke.</p>
            <p>This leſſon of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> I haue therfore the rather ſet foorthe, becauſe it teacheth vs to vnderſtand that place in <hi>Iohn</hi> figuratiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Euen ſo ſurely the ſame leſſon with the example of S. <hi>Auguſtins</hi> expoſitions therof, teacheth vs nor onlye by the ſame, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Chriſtes woordes in the Inſtitution of the Sacrament both of his body and of his blood figuratiuely, but alſo the very trewe meaning and vnderſtandinge of the ſame. For if to commaunde to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:46245:15"/>
eate the fleſhe of the ſonne of man, and to drinke his bloode, ſéem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to commaund an inconuenience and an vngodlines, &amp; is euen ſo indéed, if it be vnderſtanded as the woords doo ſtande in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſignification: and therfore muſt be vnderſtanded figuratiuelye and ſpiritually, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> dooth godly and learnedly inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete them: then ſurely Chriſte commaunding in his laſt Supper to eat his body and drinke his bloode, ſéemed to commaund in ſound of woordes as grate and euen the ſame inconuenience and vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſſe, as did his woordes in the vj. of S. <hi>Iohn:</hi> and therfore muſt euen by the ſame reaſon, be likewiſe vnderſtanded and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded figuratiuely and ſpiritually, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> did the other: Wherunto that expoſition of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> may ſeeme to be the more meete, for that Chriſte in his ſupper, to the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of eating and drinkinge of his body and blood, addeth: <hi>Doe this in remembrance of me.</hi> Which woords ſurelye were the keye that opened and reuealed the ſpirituall and godlye expoſition vnto Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I haue taried longer in ſettinge foorth the forme of <note place="margin">The Lords Cup as the Preeſts ſay.</note> Chriſtes woords vpon the Lordes cup, written by <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> then I did intend to doe. And yet in ſpeaking of the forme of Chriſts woords, ſpoken vpon his cup, commeth now to my remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the forme of woords vſed in the Latin Maſſe, vpon the Lords cup. Wherof I do not a little meruaile, what ſhould be the cauſe, ſeeing the Latin Maſſe agréeeth with the Euangeliſts and <hi>Paule,</hi> in the forme of woords ſaid vpon the bread why in the woordes ſaide vpon the Lordes cup, it differeth from them all, yea and addeth to the woordes of Chriſte ſpoken vpon the cup theſe woords, <hi>Miſterium fidei,</hi> that is, the miſterie of faithe, whiche are not red to be attributed vnto the Sacrament of Chriſtes blood, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Euangeliſts, nor in <hi>Paule,</hi> nor ſo far as I know in any other place of holye Scripture, yea and if it may haue ſome good expoſitione, yet why it ſhould not be as wel added vnto the woordes of Chriſt vpon his Bread, as vpon his Cup, ſurelye I doo not ſée the miſterie. And becauſe I ſée in the vſe of the Latin Maſſe, the Sacramente of the blood abuſed, when it is denyed vnto the laye people, cleane contrarye vnto Gods moſte certain woorde: for why, I doo beſéech thée, ſhould the Sacrament of Chriſts blood he denied vnto the lay Chriſtian more then to the Preeſte? Did not Chriſte ſhed his blood aſwel for the lay godlye man, as for the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye Preeſte? If thou wilt ſaye, yes that he did ſo. But the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the blood is not to be receiued without the offeringe vp and ſacrificinge therof vnto God the Father, bothe for the quicke and for the dead: and no man may make oblation of Chriſts blood vnto God but a Preeſt, and therfore the Preeſt alone, and that but in his Maſſe only, may receiue the Sacrament of the blood. And call you this, Maiſters, <hi>Myſterium fidei?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:46245:16"/>
Alas, alas, I feare me, this is before God, <hi>Miſterium iniquitatis,</hi> the miſterye of iniquitie, ſuch as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of, in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi> The Lord be mercifull vnto vs, and <note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 2. <hi>Praier Pſal.</hi> 67.</note> bleſſe vs, lighten his countenance vpon vs, and be mercifull vnto vs. That we may know thy waye vpon earthe, and amonge all people thy ſaluation.</p>
            <p>This kinde of oblation ſtandeth vpon Tranſubſtantiation his <note place="margin">The Maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to Chriſts paſſion.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> germaine, and they doo grow both vpon one ground. The Lord weede it out of his Vin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arde ſhortlye, if it be his bleſſed wil and pleaſure, that bitter root. To ſpeake of this oblatione, howe muche is it iniurious vnto Chriſtes paſſion?</p>
            <p>How? it can not, but with highe blaſphemy and hainous arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy, and intollerable pride, be claimed of any man, other then of Chriſte himſelfe: how muche and how plainly it repugneth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the manifeſt woords, the true ſence and meaning of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in many places, eſpecially in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi> the matter it is ſo long, and other haue written in it at large, that my minde is nowe, not to intreate therof any further.</p>
            <p>For only in this my ſcribling, I intend to ſearch out and ſet foorthe by the Scriptures (according to Godes gracious gifte of my poore knowledge) whether the true ſence and meaninge of Chriſtes woordes in the inſtitution of his holye ſupper, doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire any Tranſubſtantiation, as they cal it: or that the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of breade and wine doo remaine ſtill in the Lordes Supper and be the materiall ſubſtance of the holy Sacramente of Chriſte our Sauiours bleſſed bodye and bloode. Yet there remaineth one vaine <hi>Quidditi of Duns</hi> in this matter, the whiche becauſe ſome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardener in the anſwere to the</hi> 15. <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</hi>
               </note> that write now doo ſeeme to like it ſo well that they have ſtripped him out of <hi>Dunces</hi> duſty and darke termes, and pricked him and painted him in freſhe coloures of an eloquent ſtile: and may ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deceaue the more, excepte the errour be warelye eſchewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Duns</hi> ſaith in theſe woords of Chriſte, <hi>This is my bodye,</hi> this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne demonſtratiue, meaning the woorde <hi>(This)</hi> if ye will knowe what it dooth ſhowe or demonſtrate, whether the bread that Chriſt took or no: he anſwereth no, but onely one thing in ſubſtance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paintethe, wherof the nature or name it doothe not tell, but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that to be determined and told by that which followeth the woord <hi>Is,</hi> that is by <hi>Praedicatum,</hi> as the Logician dooth ſpeake: and therfore he calleth this pronowne demonſtratiue. <hi>(This) Indiuiduum vagum,</hi> that is, a wandring proper name, wherby we may poynte out and ſhewe anye one thing in ſubſtance, what thinge ſoeuer it be. That this imagination is vaine and vntruely applyed vnto theſe woordes of Chriſte, <hi>This is my bodye:</hi> it may appeare plainely in the woordes of <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid vpon the cup, conferred with the forme of woords ſpoken vpon the cup in <hi>Mathewe</hi> and <hi>Marke.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:46245:16"/>
For as vpon the breade it is ſaid of all. <hi>This is my bodye:</hi> ſo of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> and <hi>Mark,</hi> it is ſaide vpon the cup: <hi>This is my blood.</hi> Then if in the woords, This is my body, the woorde <hi>(This)</hi> be as <hi>Duns</hi> calleth it, a wandringe name to appoynte and ſhewe foorth any one thing, whereof the name and nature it doothe not tell: ſo muſte it be likewiſe in thoſe woordes of <hi>Mathewe</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> vpon the Lords cup <hi>This is my bloode.</hi> But in the woordes of <hi>Mathewe</hi> and <hi>Marke,</hi> it ſignifieth and poynteth out the ſame that it dooth in the Lords woords vpon the cup in <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> where it is ſaid: <hi>This cup is the new teſtament in my blood, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore in <hi>Mathewe</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> the pronown demonſtratiue <hi>(this)</hi> doothe not wander to poynte onelye one thing in ſubſtance, not ſhewinge what it is, but tellethe it plainelye what it is, no leſſe in <hi>Mathewe</hi> and <hi>Marke</hi> vnto the eye then is doon in <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paule,</hi> by putting too this woord (cup) booth vnto the eye, and vnto the eare. For taking the cup and demonſtrating or ſhewing it vnto his diſciples, by this pronowne demonſtratiue, <hi>(this)</hi> and ſaying vnto them, <hi>Drink ye all of this:</hi> it was then all one to ſaye. <hi>This is my blood;</hi> as to ſaye: <hi>This cup is my blood,</hi> meaninge by the cup as the nature of the ſpeach dooth require: the thinge conteined in the cup. So likewiſe without al doubt, when Chriſte had taken breade, giuen thanks, and broken it, and giuing it to his diſciples, ſaid, <hi>Take:</hi> and ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrating and ſhewing that bread which hee had in his bandes, to ſaye then, <hi>This is my body:</hi> and to haue ſaide, <hi>This bread is my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As it were all one, if a man lackinge a Knife, and going to his Oiſters, would ſay vnto an other, whom he ſaw to haue two kniues. Sir I praye you lend mee the one of your-kniues. Were it not now all one to anſwere him, Sir, holde I will lende you this to eat your meat, but not to open Oiſters withall: and holde, I wil lend you this Knife to eate your meat but not to open Oyſters. This ſimilitude ſerueth but for this purpoſe, to declare the nature of ſpeach withall, where as the thinge that is demonſtrated and ſhewed, is euidently perceiued, and openly knowen to the eye.</p>
            <p>But O good Lord, what a wonderfull thing is it to ſee, how ſome men doo labour to teach, what is demonſtrated and ſhewed by the pronowne demonſtratiue <hi>(this)</hi> in Chriſtes woordes when he ſaieth: <hi>This is my body: This is my blood:</hi> how they labour (I ſaye) to teache, what that <hi>(This)</hi> was then indeede, when Chriſte ſpake in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gard. to the</hi> 130. <hi>Obiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
               </note> the beginning of the ſentence the woorde <hi>(This)</hi> before he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced the reſte of the woords, that folowed in the ſame ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: ſo that their doctrine maye agree with their Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation: <note place="margin">God makers agree not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them ſelues.</note> which indeed is the verye foundation, wherein al their erronious doctrine dooth ſtande. And heere the Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours doo not agree amonge them ſelues, no more then they doo in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:46245:17"/>
the woords which wrought the Tranſubſtantiation, when Chriſte did firſt inſtitute his Sacrament: wherin <hi>Innocentius</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> of the latter daies, and <hi>Duns</hi> (as was noted before) do attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the woorke unto the woord <hi>(Benedixit)</hi> Bleſſed: but the reſt for the moſte parte, to <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum. This is my body, &amp;c. Duns</hi> therefore with his ſecte, becauſe he puttech the change before muſt needs ſay, that this, when Chriſte ſpake it in the beginning of the ſentence, was in deed Chriſtes body. For in the change, the ſubſtance of bread did depart, and the change was now doon in <hi>Benedixit</hi> (ſaith he) that went before: and therefore after him and his that <hi>(this)</hi> was then indeed Chriſtes body, though the woord did not import ſo muche but onely one thinge in ſubſtance: whiche ſubſtance after <hi>Duns</hi> (the breade beinge gone) muſt needs be the ſubſtance of Chriſts body. But they that put their Tranſubſtantiation to be wrought by theſe woordes of Chriſte. <hi>This is my bodye:</hi> and doo ſay, that when the whole ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was finiſhed then this change was perfected and not before: they can not ſay, but yet Chriſtes <hi>(this)</hi> in the beginning of the ſentence before the other woords were fully pronounced, was bread in deed. But as yet the change was not doon, and ſo long the bread muſt needs remain, and ſo longe with the uniuerſall conſent of al tranſubſtantiatours, the naturall ſubſtance of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can not come: and therefore muſt their <hi>(this)</hi> of neceſſitye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate and ſhewe the ſubſtance, which was as yet in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of the firſt woord <hi>this</hi> by Chriſte, but bread. But how can they make and verifie Chriſts woords to be true, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the ſubſtance which in the demonſtration is but bread, and ſay thereof, <hi>This is my body,</hi> that is, as they ſaye the natural ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſts body: except they would ſay, that the verbe, <hi>Is,</hi> ſignifieth, <hi>is made,</hi> or, <hi>is changed into.</hi> And ſo then if the ſame verbe, <hi>Is,</hi> be of the ſame effect in Chriſts woords ſpoken upon the cup, and rehearſed by <hi>Luke</hi> and <hi>Paule:</hi> the cup or the wine in the Cup muſte bee made or turned into the newe Teſtamente, as was declared before.</p>
            <p>There be ſome among the Tranſubſtantiatours, which walke ſo wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lye and ſo warely between theſe two aforeſaid opinions, <note place="margin">Gardener a neutrall or lack of both ſides.</note> allowing them both, and bolding plainelye nother of them bothe, that me thinks they may be called Neutrals, Ambodexters, or rather ſuche as can ſhift on both ſides. They play on both partes. For with the later, they doo allow the doctrine of the laſt ſillable, which is that Tranſubſtantiatione is doone by miracle in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, at the ſound of the laſt ſyllable <hi>(um)</hi> in this ſentence, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> And they doo allowe alſo <hi>Duns</hi> his fantaſticall ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of <hi>Individium vagum,</hi> that demonſtrateth as he teacheth in Chriſtes woords, one thing in ſubſtance, then being (after his minde) the ſubſtance of the body of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:46245:17"/>
A merhailous thinge, how one man can agrée with both theſe two, they being ſo contrary the one to the other. For the one ſaithe, the woorde <hi>this,</hi> demonſtrateth the ſubſtance of bread: and the other ſaith no not ſo, the bread is gone, and it demonſtrateth a ſubſtance whiche is Chriſtes body. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gard. to the</hi> 4. <hi>obiectiou.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Tuſhe ſaith this third man, yée vnderſtand nothing at all. They agree well inough in the chéef poynte, whiche is the ground <note place="margin">God makers agree againſt the trueth. Note.</note> of all: that is, both doth agrée and beare witnes, that there is Tranſubſtantiation. They do agrée indéed in that concluſion: I graunt. But their proceſſe and doctrine therof doo euen aſwell agrée togeather: as did the falſe witnes before <hi>Annas</hi> &amp; <hi>Caiphas</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt: or the two wicked Iudges againſt <hi>Suſanna.</hi> For againſte Chriſte the falſe witneſſes did agrée no doubt to ſpeak all againſte him. And the wicked iudges were both agréeed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne poore <hi>Suſanna:</hi> but in examination of their witneſſes, they diſſented ſo far that al was found falſe that they went about, both that wherin they agréeed, and alſo thoſe thinges, which they brought for their proofes.</p>
            <p>Thus muche haue I ſpoken, in ſearchinge out a ſolucione for <note place="margin">The conſent of the olde authors.</note> this principall queſtion, which was, what is the materiall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the holye Sacramente in the Lords ſupper? Now leaſt I ſhould ſeem to ſet by mine owne conceite, more then is méet: or leſſe to regard the doctrine of the old eccleſtaſticall writers, then is conuenient for a man of my poore learning and ſimple wit for to doo. And becauſe, alſo I am indéed perſwaded, that the olde eccleſiaſtical writers underſtood the true meaning of Chriſt in this matter: and have both ſo truly and ſo plainly ſet it foorth in certain places of their writinges, that no man whiche will vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to reade them, and without preiudice of a corrupt iudgement will indifferently weigh them, &amp; conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er their mindes none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then they declare themſelves to have mente: I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded (I ſay) that in reading of them thus no man can be ignorant in this matter, but he that wil ſhut up his own eies, and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>féeld himſelf. When I ſpeake of Eccleſiaſtical writers, I mean of ſuch as were before the wicked vſurpation of the ſee of <hi>Rome</hi> was growen ſo unmeaſurably great, that not only with tiranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal power, but alſo with corrupt doctrine, it began to ſubuert Chriſtes goſpell, and to turne the ſtate, that Chriſte and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſet in the Church, vpſide down. For the cauſes aforeſaide, I will rehearſe certain of their ſayings: and yet becauſe I take them but for witneſſes and expounders of this doctrine and not as the authors of the ſame, and alſo for that now I wil not be tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous I will rehearſe but fewe, that is thrée olde writers of the Gréeke Church, and other three of the Latin Church, which do ſeem unto me to be in this matter moſt plaine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:46245:18"/>
The Gréek Authors are <hi>Origen, Chriſoſtome</hi> and <hi>Theodoret.</hi> The Latin, are <hi>Tertulliane,</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius.</hi> I know there call be nothinge ſpoken ſo plainly, but the crafty wit furniſhed with eloquence can darken it, and weeſt it quite from the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a contrary ſence. And I know alſo that eloquence, craft, and finenes of wit hath gone about to bleare mens eies, and to ſtop their eares in the aforenamed writers, that men ſhoulde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare nor ſee, what thoſe Authors bothe write and teache ſo plainely, that excepte men ſhoulde be made both ſtarke blinde and or aſe: they can not but of neceſſitie, if they will reade and way them indifferently, both he are and ſee what they doo meane when eloquence, crafte, and fineneſſe, of wit have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all that they can. Now let us he are the olde writers of the Greeke Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origene,</hi> which lived about 1250. yéeres agoe: a man for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his learninge ſo highlye eſteemed in Chriſtes Church, <note place="margin">Origen.</note> that he was counted and iudged the ſingular teacher in his time of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle Hiſt. Li.</hi> 6. <hi>Ca.</hi> 3.</note> Chriſts religion, the confounder of hereſies, the ſchoolmaiſter of many godly matters, and an opener of highe miſteries in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He writing upon the iv chapter of Saint <hi>Mathewes</hi> goſpell, ſaieth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bus: <hi>But if any thing enter into the mouth it goeth away in to the belly, and is auoided into the draught: Yea and that meat whiche is ſanctified by the woord of God and praier, concerning the matter thereof, it goeth away into the belly, and is auoided into the draughte. But for the praier which is added vnto it, for the proportion of the faith, it is made profitable, makinge the minde able to perceive and ſee that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. For it is not the immateriall ſubſtance of breade, but the woord which is ſpoken vpon it, that is profitable to the man that eateth it not vnwoorthely. And his I mean of the Typical and Simbolical,</hi> that is, Sacramentall <hi>bodye.</hi> Thus far goe the woords of <hi>Origene,</hi> where it is plaine, firſte that <hi>Origene</hi> ſpeaking heer of the ſacrament of the Lords ſupper as the laſte woordes doo plainely ſignifie, dooth meane and teache, that the material ſubſtance therof is receiued, digeſted, and auoided, as the material ſubſtance of other bread and meats is, which coulde not be, if there were no materiall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of bread at all, as the fantaſticall opinion of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation dooth put. It is a world too ſee the anſwere of the Papiſtes to this place of <hi>Origen,</hi> in the diſputations which were in this <note place="margin">The Papiſts obiection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gene.</note> matter in the Parliamente houſe, and in both the vniuerſities of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Oxforde,</hi> they that defended Tranſubſtantiation ſaid, that this parte of <hi>Origen</hi> was but ſet forth of late by <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> and therefore is to be ſuſpected. But how vaine this their anſwere is, it appeareth plainly. For ſo maye all the good olde authors, which lay in olde libraries, and are ſet foorth of late, be by this reaſon re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cted, as <hi>Clement Alexandrinus, Theodoretus, Iuſtinus, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtica</hi> 
               <note place="margin">An other ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</note> 
               <hi>hiſtoria, Nicephori,</hi> and other ſuch. An other anſwere they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:46245:18"/>
had, ſaying that <hi>Origen</hi> is noted to haue erred in ſome poyntes, and therfore faithe is not to be giuen in this matter vnto him. But this anſwer well waighed dooth miniſter good matter to the cleere confutation of it ſelfe. For indeed we graunte, that in ſome poynts <hi>Origen</hi> did erre. But thoſe errours are gathered out and noted both of S. <hi>Ierome</hi> and <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> ſo that his woorkes (thoſe errours excepted) are now ſo much the more of authoritie, that ſuche great learned men took pains to take out of him, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they thoughte in him to be written amis. But as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge this matter of the Lords Supper, nother they nor yet euer any other anciente Author did euer ſay, that <hi>Origen</hi> did erre.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe theſe two anſwers have beene of late ſo confuted <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardener to the</hi> 166.</note> and confounded, that it is well perceiued, that they will take no place: therfore ſome whiche haue written ſince that time, haue forged two other anſwers, euen of the ſame moulde. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer whereof is, that <hi>Origen</hi> in this place ſpake not of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of bread or wine of the Lords table, but of an other miſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call meat: of the which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> maketh mencion to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto them, that were taught the faithe, before they were baptiſed. But <hi>Origens</hi> owne woordes in two ſentences before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed being put togither, prooue this anſwere vntrue. For he ſaith, that he meaneth of that figuratiue and miſticall bodye, which profiteth them, that doo receiue it woorthilye, alludinge ſo plainelye vnto S. <hi>Paules</hi> woords ſpoken of the Lords Supper: that it is a ſhame for any learned man once to open his mouth to the contrarye. And that breade which S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſpeaketh of, he can not proue that any ſuche thing was vſed in <hi>Origens</hi> time. Yea and though that coulde bee proued, yet was there neuer breade in any time called a ſacramentall body, ſauing the ſacramentall bread of the Lords table, which is called of <hi>Origen</hi> the typicall and ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall body of Chriſte.</p>
            <p>The ſecond of the two new found anſwers, is yet moſte mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <note place="margin">Gardener in the ſame place.</note> of al other, which is this. <hi>But let vs graunt</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that</hi> Origen <hi>ſpake of the Lordes Supper, and by the matter therof was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanded the materiall ſubſtance of bread and wine:</hi> what then ſay they? <hi>For thoughe the materiall ſubſtance was once gone and departed by reaſon of Tranſubſtantiation, whils the formes of the bread and the wine did remaine, yet now it is no inconuenience to ſaye, that as the material ſubſtance did departe at the entring in of Chriſtes body vnder th' aforeſaid formes, ſo whan the ſaid formes be deſtroyed and doo not remaine, then commeth again the ſubſtance of bread and wine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And this,</hi> ſay they, <hi>is very meet in this miſterye, that that which began with the miracle, ſhall ende in a miracle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I had not red this fantaſie I would ſcarcelye haue beleued, that any learned man euer would haue ſet foorth ſuch a fooliſhe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:46245:19"/>
fantaſie: which not onelye lacketh al ground, either of Gods woord, reaſon, or of any ancient writer, but alſo is clean contrary to the common rules of ſchoole diuinitie: which is, that no mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle is to be affirmed and put without neceſſitie. And although for their former miracle, which is their Tranſubſtantiation, they haue ſome colour, though it be but vaine, ſaying it is doone by the power and vertue of theſe woords of Chriſte, <hi>This is my body:</hi> yet to make this ſeconde miracle of returninge the materiall ſubſtance againe they haue no colour at al. Or els I pray them ſhew me, by what woords of Chriſte is the ſecond miracle wrought.</p>
            <p>Thus ye may ſée, that the ſleights and ſhifts which crafte and witte can inuente to wreſte the true ſence of <hi>Origen</hi> cannot take place. But now let vs heare an other place of <hi>Origen,</hi> and ſo we wil let him go.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Origen</hi> in the eleuen Homile <hi>Super Leuiticum</hi> ſaith: <hi>that there is alſo euen in the foure Goſpells, and not onelye in the olde Teſtament, a letter</hi> (meaninge a litterall ſence) <hi>whiche killethe. For if thou followe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the letter in that ſayinge: Excepte ye eate the fleſhe of the Sonne of Man, and drink his blood, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This letter dooth kill.</hi> If in that place the letter dooth kil, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is commaunded the eating of Chriſtes fleſh? then ſurelye in thoſe woordes of Chriſte, wherein Chriſte commaundeth vs to eate his body, the literall ſence therof likewiſe dooth kil. For it is no leſſe crime but euen the ſame and all one in the literall ſence, to eate Chriſtes bodye, and to eate Chriſtes fleſhe. Wherefore if the one doo kill, excepte it be vnderſtanded figuratiuelye and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituallye: then the other ſurelye doothe kill likewiſe. But that to eate Chriſtes fleſhe dooth kill ſo vnderſtanded, <hi>Origen</hi> affirmeth plainly in his woordes aboue rebearſed: Wherefore it cannot be iuſtly denied, but to eate Chriſtes bodye literally vnderſtanded, muſt néeds after him kill likewiſe.</p>
            <p>The anſwere that is made to this place of <hi>Origen</hi> of the Papiſts, is ſo fooliſh, that it be wraieth it ſelf, without any further confuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is the ſame, that they make to a piace of S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>ca.</hi> 16.</note> his book <hi>De doctrinae Chriſtiana:</hi> Whereas S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh in effecte the ſame thinge that <hi>Origen</hi> dooth héer. The Papiſts an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is this: To the carnal man the literal ſence is hurtfull, but not ſo to the ſpirituall. As though to vnderſtande that in his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſence, which ought to be taken figuratiuely, were to the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man a dangerous perill: but to the ſpirituall man none at all.</p>
            <p>Now to <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> whom I bringe for the ſecond writer in the <note place="margin">Chriſoſtome.</note> Gréek Church, He ſpeaking againſt the unholy vſinge of mans body, which after S. <hi>Paule</hi> ought to be kept pure and holy, as the very temple of the Holy Ghoſt, ſaith thus: <hi>If it be a fault</hi> (ſaith he) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In opere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. ho.</hi> 9. <hi>in Matthe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to tranſlate the holy veſſels, in the which is conteined not the trewe bodye</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:46245:19"/>
               <hi>of Chriſte, but the miſtery of the body, to private vſes, how much more offence is it to a buſe and defile the veſſels of our body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be the woordes of <hi>Chriſoſtome,</hi> But I trowe that héer many fowle ſhifts are deuiſed, to defeat this place. The Author ſaith: <hi>one is ſuſpected.</hi> I anſwere: but in this place neuer fault was found with him, vnto theſe our daies. And whether this au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was <hi>Iohn Chriſoſtome</hi> him ſelfe the Archbiſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> or no, that is not the matter. For of all it is graunted, that he was a writer of that age, and a man of great learninge: ſo that it is manifeſt, that this which he writeth was the receiued opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of learned men in his daies.</p>
            <p>Or els vndoubtedly in ſuch a matter his ſayinge ſhoulde haue <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardener to the</hi> 198. <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection:</hi>
               </note> bin impugned of ſome that wrote in his time, or neere vnto the ſame. <hi>Nay</hi> (ſaith an other) <hi>if this ſolucion wil not ſerue: we maye ſaye that</hi> Chriſoſtome <hi>did not ſpeak of the veſſels of the Lordes cup, or ſuche as were then vſed at the Lordes table, but of the veſſels vſed in the Temple in the olde lawe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This anſwer wil ſerue no more then the other. For héere <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom</hi> ſpeaketh of ſuch veſſells, wherin was that whiche was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the body of Chriſte, <hi>althoughe it was not the true body</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of Chriſte, but the miſterye of Chriſtes bodye.</hi> Now of the veſſels of the olde lawe the writers doo vſe no ſuch manner of phraſe: for their ſacrifices were not called Chriſtes body. For then Chriſt was not but in ſhadows and figures, and not by the Sacrament of his body reuealed. <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> which was a man that coulde vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the woordes and ſence of the writers, although hee would not be ſéene to ſpeak againſt this errour of Tranſubſtantiatione, becauſe he durſte not: yet in this time declareth plainly that this ſayinge of the writer is none otherwiſe to be underſtanded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yet can I</hi> (ſaithe the third Papiſt) <hi>finde out a fine and ſubtil ſoluci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gardener in the ſame place.</note> 
               <hi>for this place, and graunt all that yet is ſaide, both allowinge heere the writer, and alſo that he ment of the veſſels of the Lordes Table. For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the body of Chriſte is not conteined in them, at the Lordes Table, as in a place, but as in a miſterye.</hi> Is not this a pritty ſhifte, and a miſticall ſolution? But by the ſame ſolution then Chriſts bodye is not in the Lordes Table, nor in the Preeſtes handes, nor in the pixe, and ſo is hee heere no where. For they will not ſaye, that he is either heere or there, as in a place.</p>
            <p>This anſwere pleaſeth ſo well the maker, that he him ſelf (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had plaid with it a little while and ſhewed the fineneſſe of his wit and eloquence therein) is content to giue it ouer and ſaye: <hi>but it is not to be thought that</hi> Chriſoſtome <hi>would ſpeak after this fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or ſubtiltie:</hi> and therfore he returneth againe vnto the ſecond anſwere for his ſhoote anker, which is ſufficiently confuted before. An other ſhorte place of <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> I wil reherſe, which (if any
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:46245:20"/>
indifferency may be heard) in-plaine termes ſetteth foorth the trueth of this matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Before the bread (ſaith</hi> Chriſoſtome <hi>ad Ceſarium monachum) be ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, we call it bread, but the grace of God ſanctifying it by the meanes of the preeſte it is deliuered now from the name of bread, and eſteemed woorthy to be called Chriſts body, although the nature of bread tarry in it ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe be <hi>Chriſoſtoms</hi> woords: wherin I praye you, what can be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardener to the</hi> 202. <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection.</hi>
               </note> ſaid or thoughte more plaine againſt this errour of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, then to declare, that the breade abideth ſo ſtill: And yet to this ſo plaine a place, ſome are not aſhamed thus ſhamefully to elude it, ſaying: <hi>we graunt that nature of bread remaineth ſtil thus, for that it may be ſeene, felte, and taſted, and yet the corporal ſubſtance of the bread therfore is gone, leaſte two bodies ſhoulde be confuſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and Chriſte ſhoulde be thought impanate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What contrarietie and falſehood is in this anſwere, the ſimple man may eaſily perceiue. Is not this a plain contrarietye to graunt that the nature of bread remaineth ſo ſtill, that it may be ſéene, felte, and taſted: and yet to ſaye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the corporall ſubſtance is gon, to auoid abſurdity of Chriſts impanation? And what mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt falſhood is this, to ſaye or mean, that if the breade ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtill, then muſt followe the inconuenience of impanation?</p>
            <p>As though the very breade coulde not be a Sacrament of Chriſts body (as water is of baptiſme) excepte Chriſte ſhoulde vnite the nature of breade to his nature in vnitie of perſone, and make of the bread, God.</p>
            <p>Now let vs heare <hi>Theodoretus,</hi> which is the laſt of the thrée Gréek <note place="margin">Theodoret:</note> Authors. He writeth in his dialogue <hi>Contra Eutichen,</hi> thus. <hi>He that calleth his naturall body, corn and breade: and alſo named himſelf a Vine tree: euen he the ſame hath honoured the Symboles</hi> (that is the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dial.</hi> 1.</note> ſacramental ſignes) <hi>with the names of his body and blood, not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging indeed the nature it ſelfe, but adding grace vnto the nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can be more plainly ſaide, then this, that this olde writer ſaieth? <hi>That although the Sacraments beare the name of the body and blood of Chriſte, yet is not their nature changed, but abideth ſtill. And where is then the Papiſts Tranſubſtantiation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame writer to the ſecond dialogue of the ſame woorke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſte th' aforeſaide heretique <hi>Eutyches,</hi> writeth yet more plainly againſt this errour of Tranſubſtantiation, if any thing can be ſaide to be more plaine. For hee maketh the heretike to ſpeake thus againſte him that defendeth the true doctrine, whom he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>Orthodoxus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the Sacramentes of the bodye and bloode of our Lorde are one thinge before the inuocation, and after the inuocation they be changed, and are made an other: ſo likewiſe the Lordes body</hi> (ſaithe the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:46245:20"/>
               <hi>is after the aſſumption or aſſention into heauen, turned into the ſubſtance of God:</hi> the heretike meaninge thereby, that Chriſte after his aſcention, remaineth no more a man.</p>
            <p>To this <hi>Orthodoxus</hi> anſwereth thus and ſaith in the heretike: <hi>Thou art taken</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in thine owne ſnare. For thoſe miſticall Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bols or Sacraments after the ſanctification doo not goe out of theire owne nature, but they tarrye and abide ſtil in their ſubſtance, figure, and ſhape, yea and are ſenſibly ſeene and groped to be the ſame they were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At theſe words the papiſtes doo ſtartle: and to ſaye the trueth, theſe woordes be ſo plaine, ſo full, and ſo cléere, that they can not tell what to ſay, but yet they will not ceaſe to go about to play the cuttles, and to caſte their colours ouer them, that the trueth which is ſo plainly told, ſhould not haue place.</p>
            <p>This Author wrote (ſay they) before the determination of the Churche. As who would ſay, whatſoever that wicked man <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> the <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> determined in his congregationes with his monks and friers, that muſt be (for ſo <hi>Duns</hi> ſaith) holden for an article, and of the ſubſtance of our faith. Some doo charge this <note place="margin">D. Moreman in the Conu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation houſe.</note> author that he was ſuſpected to be a <hi>Neſtorian,</hi> which thing in <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> Counſaile was tryed and prooued to be falſe. But the fouleſt ſhift of al, and yet the beſt that they can finde in this matter, when none other will ſerue: is to ſay, that <hi>Theodoret</hi> vnderſtandeth by the woord (ſubſtance) accidents, and not ſubſtance indéed.</p>
            <p>This gloſe is like a gloſe of a lawyer, vpon a decrée, the text whereof beginning thus: <hi>Statuimus,</hi> that is, <hi>We decree.</hi> The gloſe of the Lawyer there (after many other pritty ſhifts there ſet foorth) which he thinketh will not well ſerue to his purpoſe, and therfore at the laſte to cleere the matter, he ſaith thus: after the minde of one Lawyer. <hi>Vel dic</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Statuimus id eſt, abrogamus,</hi> that is: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſtine. Ca.</hi> 4. <hi>Statuimus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>or expound we doo decree,</hi> that is, <hi>we abrogate or diſanul.</hi> Is not this a goodlye, and woorthye gloſe? who will not ſaye, but he is woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thye in the lawe, to be reteined of counſaile, that can gloſe ſo well, and finde in a matter of difficultie, ſuch fine ſhifts? And yet this is the lawe, or at leaſt the gloſe of the lawe. And therfore who can tell, what perill a man may incurre to ſpeak againſt it except he were a lawyer indeed, whiche can keep him ſelf out of the briers what winde ſoeuer blowe.</p>
            <p>Hethertoo ye haue hearde thrée writers of the Gréeke Church, not all what they doo ſaye: for that were a labour too greate for to gather, and too tedious for the Reader: But one or two places of euery one, the which how plain, how ful, and how cleere they be againſte the errour of Tranſubſtantiation, I refer it to the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the indifferent Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:46245:21"/>
And now I wil likewiſe rehearſe the ſayings of other thrée old antient writers of the Latin Church, and ſo make an end.</p>
            <p>And firſt I wil begin with <hi>Tertullian,</hi> whom <hi>Ciprian</hi> the holy mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr <note place="margin">Tertullian.</note> ſo highly eſtéemed, that whenſoeuer he would haue his book, he was wonte to ſaye: Giue vs now the Maiſter.</p>
            <p>This olde writer in his fourthe booke againſt <hi>Martian</hi> the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, ſaith thus: <hi>Ieſus made the bread, which he tooke, and diſtributed to his diſciples, his body, ſaying: This is my body. That is to ſay</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian) a figure of my body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this place it is plaine, that after <hi>Tertullians</hi> expoſition, Chriſte mente not by callinge the breade his bodye, and the wine his blood, that either the breade was the naturall bodye, or the wine his natural blood, but he called them his bodye and blood, becauſe he would inſtitute them to be vnto vs Sacramentes: that is holye tokens and ſignes of his bodye and of his blood: that by them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring and firmly belieuing the benefites procured to us by his body, which was torne and crucified for vs, and of his blood, which was ſhed for vs vpon the croſſe: and ſo with thanks receiuing theſe holy Sacramentes, according to Chriſtes inſtitution, might by the ſame be ſpiritually nouriſhed and fed to the increaſe of all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines in vs heere in our pilgrimage and iourney wherein we walke vnto euerlaſting life.</p>
            <p>This was vndoubtedlye Chriſte our Sauiours mind, and this is <hi>Tertullians</hi> expoſition.</p>
            <p>The wrangling that the Papiſts doo make to elude this ſayinge <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gardener to the</hi> 16. <hi>Obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</hi>
               </note> of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> is ſo far out of frame, that it euen werieth me to think on it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> writeth heere (ſay they) as none hath deon hithertoo before him.</p>
            <p>This ſaying is too too manifeſte falſe: for <hi>Origene, Hilarye, Ambroſe, Baſill, Grigorie, Nazianzene,</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and other old authors, likewiſe doo call the ſacrament, a figure of Chriſtes bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye. And where they ſay, that <hi>Tertullian</hi> wrote this, when he was in a heate of diſputatione with an heretike, coueting by all means to ouerthrow his aduerſarye. As who ſaye, he would not take heed, what he did ſay, and ſpecially what he would write in ſo high a matter ſo that he might haue the better hand of his aduerſarye.</p>
            <p>Is this credible to be true in any godly wiſe man? How muche leſſe then is it woorthye to be thought or credited in a man of ſo great a wit, learning, and excellency as <hi>Tertullian</hi> is worthily eſteemed euer to haue been?</p>
            <p>Likewiſe this author in his firſt booke againſte the ſame here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike <hi>Martion,</hi> writeth thus: <hi>God did not reiect bread, which is his creature<hi>:</hi> for by it he hath made a repreſentation of his body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:46245:21"/>
Now I praye you, what is this to ſay that Chriſte hath made a repreſentation (by bread) of his body, but that Chriſt had inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ordeined bread to be a Sacrament, for to repreſent unto vs his body? Now whether the repreſentatione of one thing by an other, requireth the corporal preſence of the thinge which is ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented or no: euerye man that hath vnderſtanding, is able in this poynte (the matter is ſo cleere of it ſelfe) to be a ſufficient iudge.</p>
            <p>The ſecond doctour and writer of the Latin Churche, whoſe <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> ſayinges I promiſed to ſet foorth, is S. <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> of whoſe learning and eſtimation, I neede not to ſpeake. For all the Church of Chriſte both hath and euer hath had him for a man of moſte ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler learning, witte, and dilligence, both in ſetting foorth the true doctrine of Chriſtes religion, and alſo in the defence of the ſame againſte heretikes.</p>
            <p>This author as he hath written moſte plenteouſly in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of our faith: ſo like wiſe in this argumente hee hath written at large in many of his woorkes, ſo plainly againſt this errour of Tranſubſtantiation, that the Papiſts loue leaſte to heare of him of all other writers, partely for his authoritie, and partely becauſe he openeth the matter more fully, then any other dooth.</p>
            <p>Therfore I will rehearſe more places of him then heertofore I haue doon of the other. And firſt, what can be more plaine then that which he writeth vpon the 89. Pſalme, ſpeaking of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords body and blood: and rehearſinge (as it were) Chriſtes woords to his Diſciples after this manner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is not this bodye, whiche ye doo ſee, that ye ſhall eate, nother ſhall ye drinke this blood, which the Souldiers that crucifie me, ſhall ſpill or ſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I doo commend vnto you a miſterye or a Sacrament, which ſpiritually vnderſtanded, ſhall give you life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if Chriſte had no more naturall and corporall bodies, but that one which they then preſently both heard and ſawe, nor other natural blood, but that which was in the ſame body, and the which the ſouldiers did afterward cruelly ſhed vpon the croſſe: and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this bodye nor this bloode was (by this declaration of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine)</hi> either to be eaten or drunken, but the miſterie thereof ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually to be vnderſtanded: then I conclude (if this ſaying and expoſition of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> be true, that the miſtery which the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples ſhould eate, was not the naturall body of Chriſt, but a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the ſame ſpiritually to be underſtanded.</p>
            <p>For as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaithe in his 20. book <hi>Contra Fauſtum. Ca.</hi> 21: <hi>Chriſtes fleſh and blood was in the olde Teſtament promiſed by ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes and ſignes of their ſacrifices, and was exhibited indeed and in trueth vpon the croſſe, but the ſame is celebrated by a Sacrament of remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance vpon the aulter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:46245:22"/>
And in his book, <hi>De fide ad Petrum. Ca.</hi> 19. he ſaithe, that <hi>in theſe ſacrifices,</hi> meaning of the olde law, <hi>it is ſiguratiuely ſignified<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what was then to be giuen: but in this ſacrifice it is euidentlye ſignified what is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy giuen</hi> (vnderſtanding in the ſacrifice vpon the aulter) <hi>the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance and thanks giuing for the fleſhe, which he offered for vs, and for the bloode which he ſhed for vs vpon the croſſe:</hi> as in the ſame place and euidently there it may appeare.</p>
            <p>An other euident and cleer place wher in it appeareth, that by the Sacramental bread, which Chriſte called his bodye, he ment a figure of his body. As vpon the 3 Pſalme, where S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh this in plain termes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſte did admit Iudas vnto the feaſte, in the which he commended vnto his diſciples the figure of his body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was Chriſtes laſte Supper before his paſſion, wherin he did ordeine the ſacrament of his body, as all learned men do agree.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> alſo in his 23. Epiſtle to <hi>Bonifacius</hi> teacheth, how Sacraments doo beare the names of the thinges whereof they be Sacraments, both in Baptiſme, and in the Lords table, euen as we call euery good friday, the day of Chriſtes paſſion: and euery Eaſter daye, the daye of Chriſtes reſurrection: when in very deed there was but one day wherin he ſuffred, and but one day wherin he roſe. And why doo we then call them ſo, which are not ſo indeede, but becauſe they are in like time and courſe of the yeere, as thoſe days were, wherin thoſe thinges were doone?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Was Chriſte,</hi> ſaithe ſainte <hi>Auguſtine, offered any more but once? And he offered himſelf. And yet in a Sacramente or repreſentation not onelye euerye ſolemne feaſt of Eaſter, but alſo every daye to the People he is offered: ſo that he dooth not lye that ſaith: he is euery day offered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For if Sacraments had not ſome ſimilitude or likenes of thoſe things, whereof they be Sacraments, they coulde in no wiſe be Sacraments: and for their ſimilitudes or likenes: commonly they have the names of the things, whereof they be Sacraments. Therefore as after a certaine manner of ſpeech, the Sacrament of Chriſts body, is Chriſts body; the Sacramente of Chriſtes blood, is Chriſts bloode, ſo likewiſe the Sacrament of faith is faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this maner of ſpeach, as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teacheth in his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiones <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Queſtion</hi> 57.</note> 
               <hi>Super Leuiticum</hi> and <hi>Contra Adimantum,</hi> it is ſaid in ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>that vij. eares of corne be vij. yeeres, ſeuen Kine be ſeaven yeeres, and the rock was Chriſte: and blood is the ſoule,</hi> the which laſt ſaying (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> in his booke <hi>Contra Adimantum</hi> is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanded <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap</hi> 13.</note> to bee ſpoken by a ſigne or figure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the Lord himſelfe did not ſticke to ſaye.</hi> This is my body, <hi>when</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Contra Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum. Li. Ca.</hi> 22.</note> 
               <hi>hee gaue the ſigne of his body. For we muſt not conſider in Sacramentes,</hi> ſaithe S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in an other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>what they be; but what they doo ſignifie, or they be ſigns of things, beinge one thing in themſelves, and yet ſignifying an nother thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:46245:22"/>
For <hi>the heauenly bread</hi> (ſaith he) ſpeakinge of the Sacramentall breade <hi>by ſome maner of ſpeach is called Chriſtes body, when in very deed it is the ſacramente of his body, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What can be more plaine, or more cleerly ſpoken, then are theſe places of S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> before rehearſed, if men were not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately bent to maintaine an vntrueth, and to receiue nothinge whatſoeuer dooth ſet it foorthe. Yet one place more of S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> wil I alleage, which is very cleare to this purpoſe, that Chriſtes naturall body is in heauen, and not heer corporally in the Sacrament, and ſo let him departe.</p>
            <p>In his 50. treatice, whiche he writeth vpon <hi>Iohn.</hi> he teacheth plainly and cleerly how Chriſte being both God and man, is both heer, after a certaine maner, and yet in heauen, and not heere in his naturall body and ſubſtance, which he took of the bleſſed hirgin <hi>Mary:</hi> ſpeaking thus of Chriſte and ſayinge: <hi>By his deuine Maieſtie, by his prouidence and by his vnſpeakeable and inuincible grace that is fulfilled which he ſpake: Beholde, I am with you vnto the ende of the Worlde. But as concerning his fleſh which hee took in his incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natione, as touchinge that whiche was borne of the Virgine as concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge that whiche was apprehended by the Iewes and crucified vpon a tree, and taken down from the croſſe, lapped in linnen clothes, and buried, and roſe againe, and appeared after his reſurrection, as concerninge the fleſhe, he ſaid; ye ſhall not ever haue me with you. Why ſo? For as concerning his fleſhe, he was conuerſant with his Diſciples xl. daies, and they accompanying, ſeeing and not following him, he wentvp into heaven, and is not heere. By the preſence of his deuine maieſtie he did not departe; as concerninge the preſence of his deuine maieſtie, we have Chriſte ever with us; but as concerninge the preſence of his fleſh, he ſaid truely to his diſciples; ye ſhall not ever have me with you. For as concerninge the preſence of his fleſhe, the Church had him but a few daies; nowe it holdeth him by Faith, though it ſe him not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh repeating one thing ſo often: and all to declare and teach, how we ſhould vnderſtand the maner of Chriſtes beinge heere with vs: whiche is by his grace, by his providence, and by his deuine nature, and how he is abſent by his naturall bodye whiche was born of the virgin Mary, died, &amp; roſe for us, and is aſſended into heauen, &amp; there ſitteth, as in the articles of our faith on the right hand of God, and thence (and from none other place ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> he ſhall come on the latter daye, to iudge the quick and the dead. At the which daye the righteous ſhall then lift up their heads, and the light of Gods trueth ſhal ſo ſhine: that falſhood and errours ſhall be put into perpetuall confuſion: righteouſnes ſhall haue the vpper hand, and trueth that daye ſhall beare awaye the victorye, all th' enemies therof quite ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen, to be troden vnder foot for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:46245:23"/>
O Lord, Lord, I beſeech thee haſten this day, then ſhalt thou be glorified with the glory due unto thy holy name, and unto thy deuine maieſty: and we ſhal ſing unto thee, in all ioy, and felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, laude and praiſe for euer mere. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Héer now would I make an end. For me thinks, S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> is in this matter ſo full and plaine, and of that authoritye, that it ſhould not néed after this his declaration, being ſo firmelye grounded vpon Gods woorde, and ſo well agréeinge with the other ancient Authors, to bring in for the confirmation of this matter any moe: and yet I ſaide, I would alleage thrée of the Latin Church, to teſtifie the truethe in this cauſe. Nowe therefore the laſte of all ſhal be <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> whiche was a Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> but one that was Biſhop of that See before the wicked vſurpation and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny therof ſpred and burſt out abroade into al the world. For this man was before <hi>Bonifacius,</hi> yea and <hi>Grigorye</hi> the firſte: in whoſe daies bothe corruption of doctrine and tirannicall vſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did chée flye growe, and had the vpper hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gelaſius</hi> in an Epiſtle of the two natures of Chriſte, <hi>Contra Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichen,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gelaſius.</note> writeth thus: <hi>The Sacraments of the body and blood of Chriſte, which we receiue, are godly things wherby and by the ſame wee are made partakers of the deuine nature, and yet neuertheleſſe the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or nature of the bread and wine dooth not departe nor goe away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Note theſe woords I beſéeche you, and conſider, whether any thing can be more plainely ſpoken, then theſe woordes be againſt the errour of Tranſubſtantiatione, which is the ground and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter root, wherupon ſpringe all the horrible errours before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſed.</p>
            <p>Wherfore ſeing that the falſhood dooth appeare ſo manifeſtlye, and by ſo many waies ſo plainly, ſo cléerly and ſo fullye, that no man needeth to be deceiued, but he that will not ſée, or will not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande: let vs al that doo loue the trueth, embrace it, and forſake the falſhood. For he that loueth the trueth, is of God: and the lack of the loue therof is the cauſe why God ſuffereth men to fall into errours, and to periſh therin: yea and as S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaieth, why he ſendeth vnto them illuſions, that they beleue lyes, vnto their own condemnation: becauſe (ſaithe he) they loued not the trueth. This trueth no doubte is Gods woord. For Chriſte him ſelf ſaith vnto his father: <hi>Thy woord is trueth.</hi> The loue and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.</note> light wherof almighty God our heauenly father giue vs, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en it in our harts by his holy ſpirit through Ieſus Chriſte out Lorde, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>Vincit Veritas.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="debate">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:46245:23"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>FOX</hi> 2<hi>d</hi> Volume of Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Edit. London,</hi> 1684.</head>
            <stage>Lib. 9. pag. 106. <hi>The Diſputation held at</hi> Cambridge <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Kings Commiſſioners,</hi> June 20. 1549. <hi>wherein Biſhop</hi> Ridley <hi>moderated.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>GLin.</speaker>
               <p>Well, yet once again to you, thus. The very true Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <note place="margin">P. 106.</note> of Chriſt is to be honoured, but the ſame very true Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is in the Sacrament: <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Body of Chriſt in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is to be honoured.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Wellbeloved Friends and Brethren in our Saviour Chriſt, you muſt underſtand that this Diſputation, with other that ſhall be after this, are appointed to ſearch for the plain truth of the Holy Scriptures in theſe matters of Religion, which of a long Seaſon have been hidden from us by the falſe Gloſſes of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and now in our days muſt be revealed to us Engliſhmen through the great Mercy of God principally; and ſecondarily, through the moſt gentle Clemency of our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sovereign Lord the Kings Majeſty, whom the living Lord long preſerve to reign over us in Health, Wealth and Godlineſs, to the maintenance of Gods holy Word, and to the extirpation of all blind Gloſſes of Men, that go about to ſubvert the Truth. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe therefore, that I am one that doth love the Truth, and have profeſſed the ſame amongſt you; therefore I ſay, becauſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring my mind with yours, I will here gladly declare what I think in this point now in Controverſy. Not becauſe this wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful Doctor hath any need of my help in diſſolving of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments propoſed againſt him; for as me ſeemeth, he hath anſwered hitherto very well, and Clerkly, according to the Truth of Gods Word. But now to the purpoſe, I do grant unto you (Mr. <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent)</hi> that the old Ancient Fathers do record and witneſs a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Honour and Adoration to be due unto Chriſts Body, but they ſpeak not of it in the Sacrament, but of it in Heaven, at the right hand of the Father, as holy <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Honour thou it, and then eat it;</hi> but that Honour may not be given to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:46245:24"/>
the outward ſign, but to the Body of Chriſt it ſelf in Heaven. For that Body is there only in a ſign virtually, by Grace, in the exhibition of it in Spirit, Effect and Faith, to the worthy receiver of it. For we receive virtually only Chriſts Body in the Sacrament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>How then (if it pleaſe your good Lordſhip) doth Baptiſm differ from this Sacrament? For in that we receive Chriſt alſo by Grace, and virtually.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt is preſent after another ſort in Baptiſm, than in this Sacrament; for in that he purgeth and waſheth the Infant from all kind of Sin, but here he doth feed ſpiritually the receiver in Faith with all the merits of his bleſſed Death and Paſſion; and yet he is in Heaven ſtill really and ſubſtantially. As for Example, The Kings Majeſty, our Lord and Maſter, is but in one place, whereſoever that this Royal Perſon is abiding for the time, and yet his mighty Power and Authority is every where in his Realms and Dominions: So Chriſts real Perſon is only in Heaven ſubſtantially placed, but his might is in all things created effectually. For Chriſts Fleſh may be underſtood for the Power, or inward Might of his Fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>If it pleaſe your Fatherhood, St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> do ſay, That before the Conſecration, it is but very Bread, and after the Conſecration, it is called the very Body of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Madew.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed it is the very Body of Chriſt Sacramentally af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Conſecration, whereas before it is nothing but common Bread; and yet, after that, it is the Lords Bread; and thus muſt St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> be underſtood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>The Bread after Conſecration doth feed the Soul, <hi>Ergo,</hi> The ſubſtance of common Bread doth not remain. The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is good, for St. <hi>Ambroſe, De Sacramentis,</hi> ſaith thus, After the Conſecration there is not the thing that Nature did form, but that which the bleſſing doth conſecrate. And if the Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> did turn the nature of Water; how much more then doth the Benediction of Chriſt here, both God and Man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Madew.</speaker>
               <p>That Book of St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is ſuſpected to be none of his Works.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>So all the Fathers ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>I do marvel at that, for St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in his Book of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractations maketh plain, that that was his own very Work.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:46245:24"/>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>He ſpeaketh indeed of ſuch a Book ſo intituled, to St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> but yet we do lack the ſame Book indeed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>Well, let it then paſs to other mens Judgments. What then ſay you, to holy St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> 1200 years paſt? Who ſaith, That the Bread which our Lord gave to his Diſciples, was not changed in form or quality, but in very nature, and by the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty word was made Fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Madew.</speaker>
               <p>I do anſwer thus, That this word Fleſh may be taken two ways, either for the ſubſtance it ſelf, or elſe for a natural property of a fleſhly thing. So that <hi>Cyprian</hi> there did mean of a natural Property, and not of fleſhly Subſtance. And contrariwiſe in the Rod of <hi>Aaron,</hi> where both the Subſtance, and alſo the Property was changed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>Holy St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, The Body there made by the mighty Power of Gods word, is the Body of the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>That is to ſay, That by the Word of God, the thing hath a Being, that it had not before, and we do conſecrate the Body, that we may receive the Grace and Power of the Body of Chriſt in Heaven, by this Sacramental Body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>By your Patience (my Lord) if it be a Body of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin (as St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith) which we do conſecrate as Miniſters by Gods holy Word, then muſt it needs be more than a Sacramental, or Spiritual Body; yea, a very Body of Chriſt indeed; yea, the ſame that is ſtill in Heaven, without all moving from place to place, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakably, and far paſſing our natural Reaſon, which is in this Myſtery ſo captivate, that it cannot conceive how it is there, without a lively Faith to Gods word. But let this paſs. You do grant that this Bread doth quicken or give Life, which if it do, then it is not a natural Bread, but a ſuper-ſubſtantial Bread.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>So doth the effectual and lively Word of God, which for that it nouriſheth the Soul, it doth give Life; for the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence infuſeth it ſelf unſpeakably into the faithful Receiver of the Sacrament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>How then ſay you to holy <hi>Damaſcene,</hi> a <hi>Greek</hi> Author, who as one <hi>Tritenius</hi> ſaith, flouriſhed one thouſand years paſt; he ſaith thus, The Body that is of the holy Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> is joyned to the Divinity after the Conſecration in verity; and indeed, not ſo as the Body once aſſumpted into Heaven, and ſitting on the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers right Hand, doth remove from thence and cometh down at the Conſecration time; but that the ſame Bread and Wine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:46245:25"/>
are ſubſtantially tranſumpted into the very Body and Blood of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. If (ſaith he) thou doſt not know the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how it is brought to paſs, let it be enough to thee to believe that it is done by the Operation of the Holy Ghoſt; and we do know no more, but that the living Word of God is working, and Almighty; but the very manner how, is inſcrutable to us; and no great marvel, ſaith he, for we cannot well expreſs how the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Bread, Wine or Water are tranſumpted naturally into the ſame Body and Blood of the Receiver, and be become another Body than they were before. So ſaith this great Ancient Clerk; alſo this Shew-bread with Wine and Water, are changed by the coming of the Holy Ghoſt, into Chriſts Body and Blood, and they be not two Bodies there, but very one (of Chriſt) and the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, I deny (Maſter Doctor) that <hi>Damaſcene</hi> was one thouſand years paſt: Secondarily, I ſay, That he is not to be hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den as an Ancient Father, for that he maintaineth in his Works, evil and damnable Doctrine, as the worſhipping of Images and ſuch like. Thirdly, I ſay, That indeed God by his holy Spirit, is the worker of that which is done in the Sacrament. Alſo I grant, that there is a Mutation of the common Bread and Wine ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally into the Lords Bread and Wine, by the ſanctifying of them in the Lords Word. But I deny that there is any Mutation of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances; for there is no other change there indeed, than there is in us, which when we do receive the Sacrament worthily, then are we changed into Chriſts Body, Bones and Blood, not in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but ſpiritually, and by Grace; much like as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaw the burning Coal, even ſo we ſee not there the very ſimple Bread, as it was before the Conſecration; for an Union cannot be but of two very things. Wherefore, if we be joyned to Chriſt receiving the Sacrament, then there is no Adnihilation of Bread, which is when it is reduced to nothing, as it is in your feigned Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>So I perceive you would have me to grant that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is but a Figure, which <hi>Theophylactus</hi> doth deny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay Truth, he denieth it indeed to be a Figure; but he meaneth, that it is not only a Figure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>Whereas St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, That we being many, are one Bread, he ſpeaketh not, nor meaneth one material Bread, as you do here, <hi>Ergo,</hi> he ſpeaketh of heavenly Bread. And holy <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> upon <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, That the Paſchal Lamb was a Figure, but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:46245:25"/>
the Myſtery is the verity. For the Diſciples would not have been offended to have drunk a figure of Chriſt's Blood, being well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to figures. For Chriſt did not inſtitute a figure for a figure, but the clear verity inſtead of the figure, as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, Grace and Verity was given by Chriſt. Doſt thou ſee Bread? (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome)</hi> doth it avoid or paſs as other meats do which we receive? God forbid. <hi>Ergo,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Madew.</speaker>
               <p>That ancient Clerk <hi>Origen,</hi> upon the 15th of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> ſaith thus, As touching that which is material in the Sacrament, it deſcendeth and iſſueth out as other nutriments do; but as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that which is celeſtial, it doth not ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin. Chryſoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Homily 83. upon <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, That we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be deceived of Chriſt's Word, but our natural Senſes may be deceived in this point, very ſoon and eaſily; his ſaid words can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be falſe, but our ſenſes be many times beguiled of their judgments. Becauſe therefore that Chriſt ſaid, <hi>This is my body;</hi> let us not at any hand doubt (ſaith he) but let us believe it, and well perceive it with the eyes of our underſtanding. And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a little after in that place he ſaith thus, It was not enough that he was become man, and afterwards was ſcourged for us, but alſo he did reduce and bring us to be as one body with him, not through Faith only, but in very deed alſo he maketh us his Body. And after that he ſaith, that theſe works are not of mans power. But the ſame things that he wrought in his laſt Supper, he now worketh alſo by his Precept to his right Miniſters, and we do oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy the place of the ſame Miniſters, but he it is that doth ſanctify and tranſumpt the creatures, he performeth ſtill the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. Doctor, you muſt underſtand, that in that place St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſheweth us that Chriſt delivered to us no ſenſible thing at his laſt Supper.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glin.</speaker>
               <p>Honourable Sir, by your patience I grant that he gave to his Diſciples no ſenſible thing in ſubſtance, but a thing inſenſible, his own precious Body and Blood, under the only kinds of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. And truly, as it ſeemeth, <hi>Theophylactus</hi> beſt knew the meaning of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> becauſe all Authors accept him as a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Interpreter of him. And he hath theſe ſame plain words Tranſelemented and Transformed. Alſo <hi>Theophylactus Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſuper Marcum, Cyrillus,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, That before the conſecration it is bread, but afterwards it is Chriſts very Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. In like manner St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> upon the 33d <hi>Pſalm</hi> ſaith, That
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:46245:26"/>
in the laſt Supper Chriſt did bear himſelf in his own hands. Now every man may bear the figure of his body in his own hands, but St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> ſaith it there for a Miracle. <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his fifth Book is of the ſame mind. And St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, I do remember my words, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The Law and Figures were by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but the verity and Body came by Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Well, ſay what you liſt, it is but a figurative ſpeech, like to this, If you will receive and underſtand, he is <hi>Elias,</hi> for a property, but indeed he was not <hi>Elias,</hi> but <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt. And ſo in this place Chriſt calleth it his Body, when it was very Bread. But better than the common Bread, becauſe it was ſanctified by the Word of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Langdale.</speaker>
               <p>I will prove it by another means. Chriſt did ſuffer <note place="margin">P. 109.</note> his moſt glorious paſſion for us really and ſubſtantially; <hi>Ergo,</hi> He is alſo in the Sacrament ſubſtantially. The Argument is good, becauſe that it is the ſame here that was there crucified for us; howbeit here inviſibly, indeed ſpiritually and ſacramentally, but there viſibly, and after a mortal and moſt bloody manner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Langdale,</hi> your Argument doth well conclude, in caſe that his Body were here in the Sacrament after ſuch a ſort as it was when it was betrayed: But that is not ſo; for he was betrayed and crucified in his natural body ſubſtantially and really in very deed; but in the Sacrament he is not ſo, but ſpiritually and figuratively only.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Langd.</speaker>
               <p>By your good Lordſhips favour that is not ſo, for he is there not figuratively, but verily and indeed by the power of his mighty Word, yea even his very own natural body under the Sacrament duly performed by the lawful Miniſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Madew,</speaker>
               <p>O ſay not ſo, for you ſpeak blaſphemy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Langd.</speaker>
               <p>No, no Mr. Doctor, God forbid that either I or any man elſe, ſhould be noted of blaſphemy, ſaying nothing but the very plain truth, as in my Conſcience and Learning, I do no leſs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>O Mr. <hi>Langdale,</hi> I wis it becometh you not here to have ſuch words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Langd.</speaker>
               <p>If it like your good Lordſhip, I gave not the firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of them, but only did refute that which I was unjuſtly bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened withall, as reaſon doth require, and it grieved me to hear it. He ſaith, if it pleaſe your Lordſhip, that there is a mutation or change of the Bread after it is Conſecrated; which if it be ſo, as I grant no leſs, then I would require of him, whether it be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:46245:26"/>
changed in the Subſtance or in the Accidents, or elſe in both, or in nothing? No man can juſtly ſay, that there is a change into nothing. And all ancient Fathers do agree, that the ſame acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents are there ſtill after, that were before; nor doth any Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor ſay, That there is any mutation both of the Subſtance and Accidents alſo; <hi>Ergo,</hi> The Subſtance of Bread is changed into ſome other thing that is there really preſent under the forms of Bread and Wine, which by Chriſts words muſt needs be his own Bleſſed Body.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you are deceived greatly, for there is no change either of the Subſtances, or of the Accidents; but in very deed there do come unto the Bread other Accidents, inſomuch that whereas the Bread and Wine were not ſanctified before, nor holy, yet afterwards they be ſanctified, and ſo do receive then another ſort or kind of vertue which they had not before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>Chriſt dwelleth in us by Faith, and by Faith we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <note place="margin">Pag. 118.</note> Chriſt both God and Man, both in Spirit and fleſh; that is, this Sacramental eating is the mean and way whereby we attain to the Spiritual eating, and indeed for the ſtrengthening of us to the eating of this Spiritual food was this Sacrament Ordained. And theſe words, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> are meant thus, By Grace it is my true Body, but not my fleſhly Body, as ſome of you ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rocheſt.</speaker>
               <p>I acknowledg not his real Subſtance to be there, but <note place="margin">Pag. 119.</note> the property of his Subſtance.</p>
            </sp>
            <div type="determination">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Determination of Dr.</hi> Nicholas Ridley <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Rocheſter <hi>upon</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 120.</note> 
                  <hi>the Concluſions above prefixed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>There hath been an ancient cuſtom amongſt you, that after Diſputations had in your common Schools, there ſhould be ſome determination made of the matters ſo diſputed and debated, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially touching Chriſtian Religion. Becauſe therefore it hath ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med good unto theſe worſhipful Aſſiſtants joyned with me in Commiſſion from the Kings Majeſty, that I ſhould perform the ſame at this time; I will by your favourable patience declare both what I do think and believe my ſelf, and what alſo other ought to think of the ſame. Which thing I would that afterward ye did with diligence weigh and ponder every man at home ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally by himſelf.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:46245:27"/>
The principal Grounds, or rather Head-ſprings of this matter are ſpecially five.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The firſt is the Authority, Majeſty and Verity of Holy Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſecond is the moſt certain Teſtimonies of the Ancient Catholick Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who after my judgment do ſufficiently declare this matter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The third is the definition of a Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fourth is the abominable Hereſie of</hi> Eutiches <hi>that may enſue of Tranſubſtantiation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The fifth is the moſt ſure belief of the Article of our Faith,</hi> He aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Heaven.</p>
               <div n="1" type="ground">
                  <head>The Firſt Ground.</head>
                  <p>This Tranſubſtantiation is clean againſt the words of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and conſent of the ancient Catholick Fathers. The Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſaith, <hi>I will not drink hereafter of this fruit of the Vine,</hi> &amp;c. Now the fruit of this Vine is Wine. And it is manifeſt that Chriſt ſpake theſe words after the Supper was finiſhed, as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth both in <hi>Matthew, Mark,</hi> and alſo in <hi>Luke,</hi> if they be well underſtood. There be not many places of Scripture that do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this thing, neither is it greatly material: for it is enough if there be any one plain teſtimony for the ſame. Neither ought it to be meaſured by the number of Scriptures, but by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and by the verity of the ſame. And the Majeſty of this verity is as ample in one ſhort ſentence of the Scripture, as in a thouſand.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, Chriſt took Bread, he gave Bread. In the <hi>Acts, Luke</hi> calleth it Bread. So <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it Bread after the Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Both of them ſpeak of breaking, which belongeth to the Subſtance of Bread, and in no wiſe to Chriſt's Body, for the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Ye ſhall not break a bone of him.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Do ye this in my remembrance.</hi> And again, <hi>As often as ye ſhall drink of this Cup, do it in rememberance of me.</hi> And our Saviour Chriſt in the ſixth of <hi>John,</hi> ſpeaking againſt the <hi>Capernaites,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Labour for the meat that periſheth not.</hi> And when they asked, <hi>What ſhall we do that we may work the works of God?</hi> He anſwered them thus, <hi>This is the work of God, that ye believe in him whom he hath ſent.</hi> You ſee how he exhorteth them to faith, <hi>For Faith is that work of God.</hi> Again, <hi>This is that Bread which came down from Heaven.</hi> But Chriſts Body came not down from Heaven. Moreover, <hi>He that eateth my fleſh and drinketh my blood, dwelleth in me, and I in him. My fleſh</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is meat indeed, and my blood is drink indeed.</hi> When they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:46245:27"/>
heard this, they were offended. And whil'ſt they were offended, he ſaid unto them, <hi>What if ye ſhall ſee the Son of Man aſcend up where he was before?</hi> Whereby he went about to draw them from the groſs and carnal eating. <hi>This Body,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhall aſcend up into Heaven,</hi> meaning altogether, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith. <hi>It is the Spirit that quickneth, the Fleſh profiteth nothing. The words that I ſpeak unto you, are Spirit and Life,</hi> and muſt be ſpiritually underſtood. Theſe be the Reaſons which perſwade me to incline to this Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence and Judgment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="ground">
                  <head>The Second Ground.</head>
                  <p>Now my <hi>Second Ground</hi> againſt this <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> are the Ancient Fathers a Thouſand Years paſt. And ſo far off is it, that they do confirm this Opinion of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> that plain they ſeem to me, both to think and to ſpeak the contrary.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> in many places, calleth it <hi>Bread.</hi> The places are ſo manifeſt and plain, that it needeth not to recite them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ignatius</hi> to the <hi>Philadelphians</hi> ſaith, <hi>I beſeech you, Brethren, cleave faſt unto one Faith, and to one kind of Preaching, uſing together one manner of Thanksgiving; For the Fleſh of the Lord Jeſus is one, and his Blood is one which was ſhed for us: There is alſo one Bread broken for us, and one Cup of the whole Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Irenaeus</hi> writeth thus: <hi>Even as the Bread that cometh of the Earth, receiving God's Vocation, is now no more common Bread, but Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental Bread, conſiſting of two Natures, Earthly and Heavenly; even ſo our Bodies receiving the Euchariſt, are now no more corruptible, having hope of the Reſurrection.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tertullian</hi> is very plain, for he calleth it <hi>a Figure of his Body,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> writeth to <hi>Caeſarius</hi> the Monk, albeit he be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of diverſe, yet will I read the place, to faſten it more deeply in your minds; for it ſeemeth to ſhew plainly the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Bread to remain. The words are theſe:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Before the Bread is ſanctified, we name it Bread: but by the grace of God ſanctifying the ſame, through the Miniſtry of the Prieſt, it is delivered from the Name of Bread, and is counted worthy to bear the Name of the Lord's Body, although the very ſubſtance of Bread not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding do ſtill remain therein, and now is taken not to be two Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, but one Body of the Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bread is made of many Grains. And is that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Bread, and made of Wheat? Yea, it is ſo indeed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Book of <hi>Theodoret</hi> in <hi>Greek</hi> was lately printed at <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:46245:28"/>
which if it had not been his, it ſhould not have been ſet forth there, eſpecially ſeeing it is directly againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation:</hi> For he ſaith plainly, <hi>That Bread ſtill remaineth after the Sanctification.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gelaſius</hi> alſo is very plain in this manner: <hi>The Sacrament</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which we receive of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, is a Divine Matter: By reaſon whereof, we are made partakers by the ſame of the Divine Nature, and yet it ceaſeth not ſtill to be the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine. And</hi> certes, <hi>the repreſentation and ſimilitude of the Body and Blood of Chriſt be celebrated in the action of the Myſteries,</hi> &amp;c. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, he recited certain places out of <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Cyril,</hi> which were not noted.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iſichius</hi> alſo, confeſſeth that it is Bread.</p>
                  <p>Alſo the Judgment of <hi>Bertram</hi> in this matter is very plain and manifeſt: And thus much for the <hi>Second Ground.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="ground">
                  <head>The Third Ground.</head>
                  <p>The <hi>Third Ground</hi> is the Nature of the Sacrament, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth of Three Things; that is, <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Nutrition,</hi> and <hi>Converſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As touching <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, Cyprian</hi> thus writeth: <hi>Even as of many Grains is made one Bread, ſo are we one myſtical Body of Chriſt.</hi> Wherefore Bread muſt ſtill needs remain, or elſe we deſtroy the Nature of a Sacrament.</p>
                  <p>Alſo they that take away <hi>Nutrition,</hi> which cometh by Bread, do take away likewiſe the Nature of a Sacrament: For as the Body of Chriſt nouriſheth the Soul, even ſo doth Bread likewiſe nouriſh the Body of Man. Therefore they that take away the Grains, or the Union of the Grains in the Bread, and deny the Nutrition, or Subſtance thereof, in my judgment are Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: For they take away the Similitude between the Bread, and the Body of Chriſt; for they which affirm <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> are indeed right <hi>Sacramentaries</hi> and <hi>Capernaites.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As touching <hi>Converſion,</hi> (that like as the Bread which we receive is turned into our Subſtance, ſo are we turned into Chriſt's Body) <hi>Rabanus</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> are Witneſſes ſufficient.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="ground">
                  <head>The Fourth Ground.</head>
                  <p>They who ſay, That Chriſt is carnally preſent in the <hi>Euchariſt,</hi> do take from him the Verity of Man's Nature. <hi>Eutiches</hi> granted the Divine Nature in Chriſt, but his Humane Nature he denied. So they that defend <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> aſcribe that to the Humane Nature, which onely belongeth to the Divine Nature.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="ground">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:46245:28"/>
                  <head>The Fifth Ground.</head>
                  <p>The Fifth Ground is the certain perſwaſion of this Article of Faith, <hi>He aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at the Right Hand,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord is above, even to the end of the World; but yet the verity of the Lord is here alſo. For his Body wherein he roſe again muſt needs be in one place, but his verity is ſpread abroad every where.</hi> Alſo in another place he ſaith, <hi>Let the godly alſo receive that Sacrament, but let them not be careful</hi> (ſpeaking there of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Body.) <hi>For as touching his Majeſty, his Providence, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible and unſpeakable Grace, theſe words are fulfilled which he ſpake,</hi> I am with you to the end of the World. <hi>But according to the fleſh which he took upon him, according to that which was born of the Virgin, was apprehended of the Jews, was faſtned to a Tree, taken down again from the Croſs, lapped in Linnen Cloths, was buried and roſe again, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared after his Reſurrection, ſo ye ſhall not have me always with you; and why? becauſe, that as concerning his Fleſh, he was converſant with his Diſciples forty days, and they accompanying him, ſeeing him, but not following him, he went up into Heaven, and is not here, for he ſitteth at the right hand of his Father; and yet he is here, becauſe he is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted hence, as concerning the preſence of his Divine Majeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mark and conſider well what St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>he is aſcended into Heaven, and is not here,</hi> ſaith he. <hi>Believe not them therefore which ſay that he is here ſtill in the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreover, <hi>Doubt not</hi> (ſaith the ſame <hi>Auguſtine, but that Jeſus Chriſt, as concerning the nature of his Manhood, is there from whence he ſhall come. And remember well and believe the Profeſſion of a Chriſtian man, that he aroſe from death, aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth at the Right hand of his Father, and from that Place and none other</hi> (not from the Altars) <hi>ſhall he come to judge the quick and the dead, and he ſhall come, as the Angel ſaid, as he was ſeen to go into Heaven; that is to ſay, in the ſame form and ſubſtance, unto the which he gave immortality, but changed not Nature. After this form (meaning his Humane Nature) we may not think that it is every-where.</hi> And in the ſame Epiſtle he ſaith, <hi>Take away from the Bodies limitation of places, and they ſhall be no-where; and becauſe they are no-where, they ſhall not be at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vigilius</hi> ſaith, <hi>If the Word and the Fleſh be both of one nature, ſeeing that the Word is every-where, why then is not the Fleſh alſo every-where? For when it was in Earth, then verily it was not in Heaven; and now when it is in Heaven, it is not ſurely in Earth. And it is ſo certain that it is</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:46245:29"/>
                     <hi>not in Earth, that as concerning the ſame, we look for him from Heaven; whom as concerning the Word, we believe to be with us in Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alſo the ſame <hi>Vigilius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Which things, ſeeing they be ſo, the courſe of the Scripture muſt be ſearched of us, and many Teſtimonies muſt be gathered, to ſhew plainly what a wickedneſs and ſacriledg it is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer thoſe things to the property of the Divine Nature, which do only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the nature of the Fleſh; and contrariwiſe, to apply thoſe things to the nature of the Fleſh, which do properly belong to the Divine Nature.</hi> Which thing the <hi>Tranſubſtantiators</hi> do, whilſt they affirm Chriſt's Body not to be contained in any one place, and aſcribe that to his Humanity, which properly belongeth to his Divinity, as they do who will have Chriſt's Body to be in no one certain place limited.</p>
                  <p>Now in the latter Concluſion concerning the Sacrifice, becauſe it dependeth upon the firſt, I will in few words declare what I think. For if we did once agree in that, the whole Controverſie in the other would ſoon be at an end. Two things there be which do perſwade me that this Concluſion is true; that is, certain places of the Scripture, and alſo certain Teſtimonies of the Fathers. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>Hebrews</hi> the 9th, <hi>Chriſt being become an High Prieſt of good things to come, by a greater and more perfect Tabernacle not made with hands, that is, not of this building, neither by the Blood of Goats and Calves, but by his own Blood, entred once into the Holy Place, and obtained for us eternal Redemption,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And now in the end of the World he hath appeared once to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf.</hi> And again, <hi>Chriſt was once offered to take away the ſins of many.</hi> Moreover he ſaith, <hi>With one offering hath he made perfect for ever thoſe that are ſanctified.</hi> Theſe Scriptures do perſwade me to believe that there is no other oblation of Chriſt (albeit I am not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant there are many Sacrifices) but that which was once made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Croſs.</p>
                  <p>The Teſtimonies of the Ancient Fathers, which confirm the ſame, are out of <hi>Auguſtine ad Bonif. Epiſt.</hi> 23. Again, in his Book of 43 Queſtions, in the 41ſt Queſtion. Alſo in his 20th Book againſt <hi>Fauſtus</hi> the <hi>Manichee,</hi> Chap. 21. And in the ſame Book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſaid <hi>Fauſtus,</hi> Chap. 28. thus he writeth; <hi>Now the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians keep a memorial of the Sacrifice paſt, with a holy Oblation and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> in his Book <hi>De fide,</hi> calleth the ſame Oblation a Commemoration. And theſe things are ſufficient for this time for a Scholaſtical Determination of theſe matters.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="volume">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:46245:29"/>
            <head>VOL. III.</head>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Ridley<hi>'s Anſwer to the Three Propoſitions propoſed to him in the Diſputation at</hi> Oxford, April 12. 1554.</head>
               <p>I Received of you the other day, Right Worſhipful Mr. <hi>Prolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor,</hi> and ye my Reverend Maſters, Commiſſioners from the Queens Majeſty and her Honourable Council, Three Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; whereunto ye commanded me to prepare againſt this day, what I thought good to anſwer concerning the ſame.</p>
               <p>Now whilſt I weighed with my ſelf, how great a charge of the Lord's Flock was of late committed unto me, for the which I muſt once render an account to my Lord God, (and that how ſoon, he knoweth) and that moreover, by the Commandment of the Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> I ought to be ready alway to give a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Hope that is in me, with Meekneſs and Reverence unto every one that ſhall demand the ſame. Beſides this, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering my Duty to the Church of Chriſt, and to your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, being Commiſſioners by Publick Authority, I determined with my ſelf to obey your Commandment, and ſo openly to declare unto you my mind touching the foreſaid Propoſitions; and albeit plainly to confeſs unto you the Truth in theſe things which ye now demand of me. I have thought otherwiſe in times paſt, than now I do, yet (God I call to record unto my Soul, I lye not) I have not altered my Judgment, as now it is, either by conſtraint of any Man or Laws; either for the dread of any dangers of this World; either for any hope of Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity; but only for the love of the Truth revealed unto me by the Grace of God (as I am undoubtedly perſwaded) in his holy Word, and in the reading of the Ancient Fathers.</p>
               <p>Theſe things I do rather recite at this preſent, becauſe it may happen to ſome of you hereafter, as in times paſt it hath done to me: I mean, if ye think otherwiſe of the matters propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe Propoſitions than I now do, God may open them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in time to come.</p>
               <p>But howſoever it ſhall be, I will in few words do that which I think ye all look I ſhould do; that is, as plainly as I can, I will declare my Judgment herein. Howbeit of this I would ye were not ignorant, that I will not indeed wittingly and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:46245:30"/>
ſpeak in any Point againſt Gods Word, or diſſent in any one jot from the ſame, or from the Rules of Faith, or Chriſtian Religion; which Rules that ſame moſt Sacred word of God preſcribeth to the Church of Chriſt, whereunto I now, and for ever ſubmit my ſelf and all my doings. And becauſe the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I have now taken in hand is weighty, and ye all well know how unready I am to handle it accordingly, as well for lack of time, as alſo lack of Books; therefore here I proteſt, that I will publickly this day require of you, that it may be lawful for me concerning all mine Anſwers, Explications, and Confirmations, to add or diminiſh whatſoever ſhall ſeem hereafter more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient and meet for the purpoſe, through more ſound Judgment, better Deliberation, and more exact Trial of every particular Thing. Having now by the way of Preface and Proteſtation ſpoken theſe few words, I will come to the Anſwer of the Propoſitions propounded unto me, and ſo to the moſt brief Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and Confirmation of mine Anſwers.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                  <p>Reverend Mr. Doctor, concerning the lack of Books, there is no cauſe why you ſhould complain<hi>:</hi> What Books ſoever you will name, you ſhall have them; and as concerning the Judgment of your Anſwers to be had of your ſelf with further deliberation, it ſhall, I ſay, be lawful for you until Sunday next to add unto them what you ſhall think good your ſelf. My mind is, that we ſhould uſe ſhort Arguments, leſt we ſhould make an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite proceſs of the thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ridley.</speaker>
                  <p>There is another thing beſides, which I would gladly obtain at your hands; I perceive that you have Writers and Notaries here preſent. By all likelihood our Diſputations ſhall be publiſhed; I beſeech you for Gods ſake let me have liberty to ſpeak my mind freely, and without interruption, not becauſe I have determined to protract the time with a ſolemn Preface, but leſt it may appear that ſome be not ſatisfied. God wot I am no Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, nor have I learned Rhetorick to ſet Colours on the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                  <p>Among this whole Company, it ſhall be permitted you to take two for your part.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                  <p>I will chuſe two, if there were any here with whom I were acquainted.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                  <p>Here are two which Mr. <hi>Cranmer</hi> had yeſterday; take them if it pleaſe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                  <p>I am content with them, I truſt they are honeſt men.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="proposition">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:46245:30"/>
               <head>The Firſt Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Sacrament of the Altar, by the virtue of God's Word ſpoken of the Prieſt, the Natural Body of Chriſt, born of the Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>and his Natural Blood is Really Preſent under the Forms of Bread and Wine.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Anſwer of</hi> N. Ridley.</head>
                  <p>In matters appertaining to God we may not ſpeak according to the ſenſe of Man, nor of the World. Therefore this Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or Concluſion is framed after another manner of Phraſe or kind of Speech than the Scripture uſeth. Again it is very obſcure and dark by means of ſundry words of doubtful ſignification. And being taken in the ſenſe which the Schoolmen teach, and at this time the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth defend, it is falſe and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, and plain contrary to the Doctrine which is according to Godlineſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>The Explication.</head>
                  <p>How far the diverſity and newneſs of the Phraſe in all this firſt Propoſition, is from the Phraſe of the Holy Scripture, and that in every part almoſt, it is ſo plain and evident to any that is but meanly exerciſed in Holy Writ, that I need not now (eſpecially in this Company of Learned Men) to ſpend any time therein, except the ſame ſhall be required of me hereafter.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, There is a double ſenſe in theſe words <hi>(by virtue of God's Word)</hi> for it is doubtful what word of God this is; whether it be that which is read in the Evangeliſts, or in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or any other. And if it be that which is in the Evangeliſts, or in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> what that is. If it be in none of them, then how it may be known to be God's Word, and of ſuch virtue that it ſhould be able to work ſo great a matter.</p>
                  <p>Again, There is a doubt of theſe words <hi>(of the Prieſt)</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther no man may be called a Prieſt, but he who hath Authority to make a Propitiatory Sacrifice for the quick and the dead; and how it may be proved that this Authority was committed of God to any man, but to Chriſt alone.</p>
                  <p>It is likewiſe doubted after what Order the Sacrificing Prieſt ſhall be, whether after the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> or elſe after the Order of <hi>Melchiſedech;</hi> for as far as I know, the Holy Scripture doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low no more.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                     <p>Let this be ſufficient.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>If we lack time at this preſent, there is time enough hereafter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe are but evaſions or ſtarting holes; you conſume the time in vain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:46245:31"/>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot ſtart from you, I am captive and bound.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                     <p>Fall to it, my Maſters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smith.</speaker>
                     <p>That which you have ſpoken may ſuffice at this preſent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me alone, I pray you, for I have not much to ſay behind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Go forward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>Moreover, there is ambiguity in this word <hi>Really,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be taken as the <hi>Logicians</hi> term it <hi>tranſcendenter,</hi> that is, moſt generally, and ſo it may ſignifie any manner of thing, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the Body of Chriſt by any means; after which ſort we alſo grant Chriſt's Body to be really in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, (as in Diſputation, if occaſion be given, ſhall be declared) or whether it be taken to ſignifie the very ſame thing, having Body, Life, and Soul, which was aſſumed and taken of the Word of God, into the Unity of Perſon. In which ſenſe, fith the Body of Chriſt is really in Heaven, becauſe of the true manner of his Body, it may not be ſaid to be here in the earth. There is yet a further doubtfulneſs in theſe words <hi>under the forms of Bread and Wine,</hi> whether the forms be there taken to ſignifie the only accidental and outward ſhews of Bread and Wine; or there withal the ſubſtantial Natures thereof, which are to be ſeen by their qualities, and perceived by exterior ſenſes.</p>
                     <p>Now the Error and Falſeneſs of the Propoſition after the ſenſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church and Schoolmen, may hereby appear, in that they affirm the Bread to be Tranſubſtantiated, and changed to the Fleſh aſſumed of the Word of God; and that, as they ſay, by virtue of the Word, which they have deviſed by a certain number of words, and cannot be found in any of the Evangeliſts, or in S <hi>Paul;</hi> and ſo they gather that Chriſt's Body is really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Sacrament of the Altar: Which Poſition is ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Foundation of the Tranſubſtantiation; which Foundation is monſtrous, againſt Reaſon, and deſtroyeth the Analogy or Proportion of the Sacraments; and therefore this Propoſition alſo, which is built upon this rotten Foundation, is falſe, erroneous, and to be counted as a deteſtable Hereſie of the Sacramentaries.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                     <p>We loſe time. <hi>Ridley.</hi> You ſhall have time enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Fall to reaſoning. You ſhall have ſome other day for this matter. <hi>Rid.</hi> I have no more to ſay concerning my Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. If you will give me leave, and let me alone, I will but ſpeak a word or two for my confirmation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:46245:31"/>
                     <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                     <p>Go to, ſay on.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="confirmation">
                  <head>The Confirmation of the aforeſaid Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>There ought no Doctrine to be eſtabliſhed in the Church of <note place="margin">Teſ-</note> God, which diſſenteth from the Word of God, from the Rule of Faith, and draweth with it many abſurdities that cannot be avoided.</p>
                  <p>But this Doctrine of the firſt Propoſition is ſuch. <note place="margin">ti-no.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> It ought not to be eſtabliſhed and maintained in the Church of God.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Major</hi> or firſt part of my Argument is plain, and the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor or ſecond part is proved thus.</p>
                  <p>The Doctrine maintaineth a real, corporal, and carnal pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſt's Fleſh, aſſumed and taken of the Word, to be in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper, and that not by virtue and Grace only, but alſo by the whole Eſſence and Subſtance of the Body and Fleſh of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But ſuch a preſence diſagreeth from God's Word, from the Rule of Faith, and cannot but draw with it many abſurdities.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> The ſecond part is true.</p>
                  <p>The firſt part of this Argument is manifeſt, and the ſecond may yet futher be confirmed thus.—</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſton.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus you conſume time, which might be better be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on other matters. Mr. <hi>Opponent,</hi> I pray you, to your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smith.</speaker>
                     <p>I will here reaſon with you upon <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which you ſay is contrary to the Rule and Analogy of Faith. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary whereof I prove by the Scriptures and the Doctors. But before I enter Argumentation with you, I demand firſt, whether in the ſixth Chapter of <hi>John</hi> there be any mention made of the Sacrament, or of the Real Preſence of Chriſt in the Sacrament?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>It is againſt reaſon that I ſhould be impeached to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that which I have to ſpeak in this Aſſembly, being not ſo long, but that it may be comprehended in few words.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Let him read on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt of all, this Preſence is contrary to many places of the holy Scripture. Secondly, It varieth from the Articles of the Faith. Thirdly, It deſtroyeth and taketh away the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lord's Supper. Fourthly, It maketh precious things common to prophane and ungodly perſons; for it caſteth that which is holy unto Dogs, and pearls unto Swine. Fifthly, It forceth men to maintain many Monſtrous Miracles without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:46245:32"/>
and Authority of God's Word. Sixthly, It giveth occaſion to the Hereticks which erred concerning the two Natures in Chriſt, to defend their Hereſies thereby. Seventhly, It falſifieth the ſayings of the Godly Fathers; it falſifieth alſo the Catholick Faith of the Church which the Apoſtles taught, the Martyrs confirmed, and the Faithful (as one of the Fathers ſaith) do retain and keep until this day. Wherefore the 2<hi>d</hi> part of mine Argument is true. <hi>The Probation of the Antecedent or former part of this Argument, by the Parts thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. This carnal Preſence is contrary to the Word of God, as appeareth, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. <hi>I tell you the truth. It is profitable to you that I go away, for if I go not away, the Comforter ſhall not come unto you.</hi> Act. 3. <hi>Whom the Heavens muſt receive until the time of reſtoring of all things which God hath ſpoken.</hi> Mat. 9. <hi>The Children of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom cannot mourn ſo long as the Bridegroom is with them.</hi> But now is the time of mourning. Joh. 16. <hi>But I will ſee you again, and your hearts ſhall rejoice.</hi> Joh. 14. <hi>I will come again and take you to my ſelf.</hi> Mat. 24. <hi>If they ſhall ſay unto you, Behold here is Chriſt, or there is Chriſt, believe them not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. It varieth from the Articles of the Faith, <hi>He aſcended into Heaven, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father, from whence</hi> (and not from any other place, ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine) he ſhall come to judg both the quick and the dead.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="3">3. It deſtroyeth and taketh away the Inſtitution of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which was commanded only to be uſed and continued until the Lord himſelf ſhould come. If therefore he be really preſent in the body of his fleſh, then muſt the Supper ceaſe: For a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance is not of a thing preſent, but of a thing paſt and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. And there is a difference between Remembrance and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and (as one of the Fathers ſaith) <hi>A Figure is in vain where the thing figured is preſent.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It maketh precious things common to prophane and ungodly Perſons, and conſtraineth men to confeſs many abſurdities. For it affirmeth, that Whoremongers and Murtherers, yea, and (as ſome of them hold opinion) that Mice, Rats and Dogs alſo may receive the very real and corporal Body of the Lord, wherein the fulneſs of the Spirit of Light and Grace dwelleth; contrary to the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt words of Chriſt in ſix Places and Sentences of the 6th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of St. <hi>John.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="4">4. It confirmeth alſo and maintaineth that beaſtly kind of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty of the <hi>Anthropophagi,</hi> that is, the Devourers of Man's Fleſh: for
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:46245:32"/>
it is a more cruel thing to devour a quick Man, that to ſlay him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pie.</speaker>
                     <p>He requireth time to ſpeak Blaſphemies. Leave your Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>I had little thought to have had ſuch reproachful words at your hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſt.</speaker>
                     <p>All is quiet. Go to your Arguments Mr. Doctor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>I have not many things more to ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Weſt.</speaker>
                     <p>You utter Blaſphemies with a moſt impudent face; leave off (I ſay) and get you to the Argument.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p n="5">5. It forceth men to maintain many monſtrous Miracles, without any neceſſity and authority of God's Word. For at the coming of this preſence of the Body and Fleſh of Chriſt, they thruſt away the Subſtance of Bread, and affirm that the Accidents remain without any Subject, and inſtead thereof they place Chriſt's Body without his qualities, and the true manner of a Body. And if the Sacrament be reſerved ſo long until it mould, and Worms breed, ſome ſay that the Subſtance of Bread miraculouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turneth again, and ſome deny it. Other ſome affirm, that the real Body of Chriſt goeth down into the Stomach of the Receivers, and doth there abide ſo long only as they ſhall continue to be good; but another ſort hold that the Body of Chriſt is carried into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſo ſoon as the forms of Bread be bruiſed with the Teeth. O Works of Miracles! Truly, and moſt truly, I ſee that fulfilled in theſe Men, whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> propheſied, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Becauſe they have not received the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved, God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye, and be all damned which have not believed the Truth.</hi> This groſs Preſence hath brought forth that fond phantaſie of Concomitance, whereby is broken at this day and abrogated the Commandment of the Lord for diſtributing of the Lord's Cup to the Laity.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. It giveth occaſion to Hereticks to maintain and defend their Errors; as to <hi>Marcion,</hi> who ſaid that Chriſt had but a Phantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body; and to <hi>Eutiches,</hi> who wickedly confounded the two Natures in Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Finally, It falſifieth the Sayings of the Godly Fathers, and the Catholick Faith of the Church, which <hi>Vigilius,</hi> a Martyr and grave Writer, ſaith, was taught of the Apoſtles, confirmed with the Blood of Martyrs, and was continually maintained by the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful until his time. By the Sayings of the Fathers, I mean of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin, Irenaeus, Tertullian, Origen, Euſebius, Emiſenus, Athanaſius, Cyril, Epiphanius, Hierome, Chryſoſtome, Auguſtine; Vigilius, Fulgentius, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram,</hi>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:46245:33"/>
and others moſt ancient Fathers. All thoſe places, as I am ſure I have read, making for my purpoſe; ſo am I well aſſured that I could ſhew the ſame, if I might have the uſe of mine own Books, which I will take to me to do, even upon the peril of my life, and loſs of all that I may loſe in this World.</p>
                     <p>But now (my Brethren) think not becauſe I diſallow that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence which the firſt Propoſition maintaineth (as a Preſence which I take to be forged, Phantaſtical, and beſides the Authority of God's Word, perniciouſly brought into the Church by the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts)</hi> that I therefore go about to take away the true Preſence of Chriſt's Body in his Supper rightly and duly adminiſtred, which is grounded upon the Word of God, and made more plain by the Commentaries of the Faithful Fathers. They that think ſo of me, the Lord knoweth how far they are deceived; and to make the ſame evident unto you, I will in few words declare what true Preſence of Chriſt's Body in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper I hold and affirm, with the Word of God and the Ancient Fathers.</p>
                     <p>I ſay and confeſs with the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke,</hi> and Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> that the Bread on the which thanks are given, is the Body of Chriſt, in the remembrance of him and his Death, to be ſet forth perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually of the Faithful until his coming.</p>
                     <p>I ſay and confeſs the Bread which we break, to be the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and partaking of Chriſt's Body, with the Ancient and the Faithful Fathers.</p>
                     <p>I ſay and believe that there is not only a ſignification of Chriſt's Body ſet forth by the Sacrament, but alſo that therewith is given to the Godly and Faithful the Grace of Chriſt's Body, that is, the food of Life and Immortality. And this I hold with <hi>Cyprian.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I ſay alſo with St. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> that we eat Life, and we drink Life; with <hi>Emiſene,</hi> that we feel the Lord to be preſent in Grace; with <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that we receive Celeſtial Food that cometh from above; the propriety of natural Communion, with <hi>Hilary;</hi> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Fleſh, and Benediction which giveth life in Bread and Wine, with <hi>Cyril;</hi> and with the ſame <hi>Cyril,</hi> the virtue of the very Fleſh of Chriſt, Life and Grace of his Body, the property of the only begotten, that is to ſay Life, as he himſelf in plain words ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded it.</p>
                     <p>I confeſs alſo with <hi>Baſil,</hi> that we receive the myſtical Advent and coming of Chriſt, Grace and Virtue of his very Nature; the Sacrament of his very Fleſh, with <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> the Body by Grace, with <hi>Epiphanius;</hi> Spiritual Fleſh, but not that which was
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:46245:33"/>
crucified, with <hi>Hierom;</hi> Grace flowing into a Sacrifice, and the Grace of the Spirit, with <hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> Grace and inviſible Veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Grace and Society of the Members of Chriſt's Body, with <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Finally, with <hi>Bertram,</hi> (who was the laſt of all theſe) I confeſs that Chriſt's Body is in the Sacrament in this reſpect; namely, as he writeth, Becauſe there is in it the Spirit of Chriſt, that is, the power of the Word of God, which not only feedeth the Soul, but alſo cleanſeth it. But of theſe I ſuppoſe it may appear unto all men how far we are from that Opinion, whereof ſome go about falſly to ſlander us to the world, ſaying, we teach that the Godly and Faithful ſhould receive nothing elſe at the Lord's Table, but a Figure of the Body of Chriſt.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="proposition">
               <head>The Second Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>After the Conſecration, there remaineth no Subſtance of Bread and Wine, neither any other Subſtance, than the Subſtance of God and Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>The ſecond Concluſion is manifeſtly falſe, directly againſt the Word of God, the Nature of the Sacrament, and the moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Teſtimonies of the godly Fathers; and it is the rotten Foundation of the other two Concluſions propounded by you, both of the firſt, and alſo of the third. I will not therefore now tarry upon any further Explication of this Anſwer, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with that which is already added afore to the Anſwer of the firſt Propoſition.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The Firſt Argument for the Confirmation of this Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>It is very plain by the Word of God, that Chriſt did give Bread unto his Diſciples, and called it his Body.</p>
                  <p>But the Subſtance of Bread is another manner of Subſtance, than is the Subſtance of Chriſt's Body, God and Man.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Concluſion is falſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part of mine Argument is plain, and the firſt is proved thus.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>The Second Argument.</head>
                  <p>That which Chriſt did take, on the which he gave Thanks, <note place="margin">Da-</note> and the which he brake, he gave to his Diſciples, and called it his Body.</p>
                  <p>But he took Bread, gave Thanks on Bread, and brake Bread. <note place="margin">ti-</note> 
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> The firſt part is true.</p>
                  <p>And it is confirmed with the Authorities of the Fathers, <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">ſi-</note> 
                     <hi>Tertullian, Origen, Cyprian, Epiphanius, Hierom, Auguſtine, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret,</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:46245:34"/>
                     <hi>Cyril, Rabanus</hi> and <hi>Bede;</hi> whoſe places I will take upon me to ſhew moſt manifeſt in this behalf, if I may be ſuffered to have my Books, as my requeſt is.</p>
                  <p>Bread is the Body of Chriſt. <hi>Ergo.</hi> It is Bread.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <head>The Third Argument.</head>
                  <p>As the Bread of the Lord's Table is Chriſt's natural Body, ſo <note place="margin">Ba-</note> it is his myſtical Body.</p>
                  <p>But it is not Chriſt's myſtical Body by Tranſubſtantiation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> It is not his natural Body by Tranſubſtantiation. <note place="margin">ro- eo.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond part of my Argument is plain, and the firſt is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thus: As Chriſt, who is the Verity, ſpake of the Bread, <hi>This is my Body which ſhall be betrayed for you;</hi> ſpeaking there of his natural Body: even ſo St. <hi>Paul,</hi> moved with the ſame Spirit of Truth, ſaid, <hi>We, though we be many, yet are we all one Bread and one Body, which be partakers of one Bread.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>The Fourth Argument.</head>
                  <p>We may no more believe Bread to be Tranſubſtantiate into the Body of Chriſt, than the Wine into his Blood.</p>
                  <p>But the Wine is not Tranſubſtantiate into his Blood:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> Neither is that Bread therefore Tranſubſtantiate into his Body.</p>
                  <p>The firſt part of this Argument is manifeſt, and the ſecond part is proved out of the Authority of God's Word in <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Mark, I will not drink of the fruit of the Vine,</hi> &amp;c. Now the fruit of the Vine was Wine which Chriſt drank, and gave to his Diſciples to drink. With this Sentence agreeth plainly the place of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> on the <hi>20th</hi> Chapter of <hi>Matthew,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> doth alſo, affirming, That there is no Blood, if Wine be not in the Cup.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <head>The Fifth Argument.</head>
                  <p>The words of Chriſt ſpoken upon the Cup, and upon the <note place="margin">Ba-</note> Bread, have like effect and working.</p>
                  <p>But the words ſpoken upon the Cup have not virtue to Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiate. <note place="margin">ro-</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> It followeth that the words ſpoken upon the Bread have <note place="margin">eo.</note> no ſuch virtue.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond part of the Argument is proved; becauſe they would then Tranſubſtantiate the Cup, or that which is in the Cup, into the New Teſtament. But neither of theſe things can be done, and very abſurd it is to confeſs the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:46245:34"/>
                  <head>The Sixth Argument.</head>
                  <p>The Circumſtances of the Scripture, the Analogy and proportion of <note place="margin">Da-</note> the Sacraments, and the Teſtimony of the faithful Fathers, ought to rule us in taking the meaning of the Holy Scripture touching the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</p>
                  <p>But the Words of the Lord's Supper, the Circumſtances of the <note place="margin">ti-</note> Scripture, the Analogy of the Sacraments, and the Sayings of the Fathers, do moſt effectually and plainly prove a figurative ſpeech in the words of the Lord's Supper.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> A figurative ſenſe and meaning is ſpecially to be received in <note place="margin">ſi.</note> theſe words, <hi>This is my Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Circumſtances of the Scripture, <hi>Do this in remembrance of me. As oft as ye ſhall eat of this Bread, and drink of this Cup, ye ſhall ſhew forth the Lord's death. Let a man prove himſelf, and ſo eat of this bread, and drink of this cup. They came together to break Bread: and they continued in breaking of Bread. The Bread which we break,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For we being many, are all one Bread and one Body,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>The Analogy of the Sacraments is neceſſary; for if the Sacraments had not ſome ſimilitude, or likeneſs of the things whereof they be Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, they could in no wiſe be Sacraments. And this ſimilitude in the Sacrament of the Lord's Supper is taken three manner of ways.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The firſt conſiſteth in nouriſhing, as you ſhall read in <hi>Rabanus, Cyprian, Auſtin, Irenaeus,</hi> and moſt plainly in <hi>Iſidore</hi> out of <hi>Bertram.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. The ſecond in the uniting and joyning of many into one, as <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> teacheth.</item>
                     <item>3. The third is a ſimilitude of unlike things: Where, like as the Bread is turned into one Body; ſo we by the right uſe of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are turned through Faith into the Body of Chriſt.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The ſayings of the Fathers declare it to be a figurative ſpeech, as it appeareth in <hi>Origen, Tertullian, Chryſoſtom in opere imperfecto, Auguſtin, Ambroſe, Baſil, Gregory Nazianzen, Hilary,</hi> and moſt plainly of all, in <hi>Bertram.</hi> Moreover the ſayings and places of all the Fathers, whoſe names I have before recited againſt the aſſertion of the firſt Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, do quite overthrow Tranſubſtantiation. But of all moſt evidently and plainly, <hi>Irenaeus, Origen, Cyprian, Chryſoſtom</hi> to <hi>Caeſarius</hi> the Monk, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> againſt <hi>Adamantus, Gelaſius, Cyril, Epiphanius, Chryſoſtom</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain on the 20th of <hi>Matth. Rabanus, Damaſcene</hi> and <hi>Bertram.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here, Right Worſhipful Mr. Prolocutor, and ye the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, it may pleaſe you to underſtand, that I do not lean to theſe things only, which I have written in my former Anſwers and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmations, but that I have alſo for the proof of that I have ſpoken,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:46245:35"/>
whatſoever <hi>Bertram,</hi> a man Learned, of ſound and upright Judgment, and ever counted a Catholick for theſe Seven hundred years, until this our age, hath written. His Treatiſe, whoſoever ſhall read and weigh, conſidering the time of the Writer, his Learning, Godlineſs of life, the Allegations of the Ancient Fathers, and his manifold and moſt grounded Arguments, I cannot (doubtleſs) but much marvel, if he have any fear of God at all, how he can with good Conſcience ſpeak againſt him in this matter of the Sacrament. This <hi>Bertram</hi> was the firſt that pulled me by the Ear, and that firſt brought me from the common Error of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and cauſed me to ſearch more diligently and exactly both the Scriptures and the Writings of the old Eccleſiaſtical Fathers in this matter. And this I proteſt before the face of God, who knoweth that I lye not in the things I now ſpeak.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="proposition">
               <head>The Third Propoſition.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Maſs is the lively Sacrifice of the Church, propitiable and available for the ſins as well of quick as of the dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The Anſwer to this Propoſition.</head>
                  <p>I anſwer to this third Propoſition as I did to the firſt. And more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over I ſay, that being taken in ſuch ſenſe as the words ſeem to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, it is not only erroneous, but withal ſo much to the deroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and defacing of the Death and Paſſion of Chriſt, that I judge it may and ought moſt worthily to be counted wicked and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous againſt the moſt precious Blood of our Saviour Chriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="commentary">
                  <head>The Explication.</head>
                  <p>Concerning the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Maſs which is uſed at this day, or the lively Sacrifice thereof propitiatory and available for the ſins of the quick and the dead, the Holy Scripture hath not ſo much as one ſyllable.</p>
                  <p>There is ambiguity alſo in the name of Maſs: what it ſignifieth, and whether at this day there be any ſuch indeed as the Ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers uſed; ſeeing that now there be neither <hi>Catecumeni</hi> nor <hi>Poenitentes</hi> to be ſent away.</p>
                  <p>Again, touching theſe words <hi>(The lively Sacrifice of the Church)</hi> There is doubt whether they are to be underſtood Figuratively and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally, for the Sacrament of the lively Sacrifice (after which ſort we deny it not to be in the Lord's Supper) or properly and without any figure; of the which manner there was but one only Sacrifice, and that once offered, namely upon the Altar of the Croſs.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, in theſe words <hi>(as well as)</hi> it may be doubted whether they be ſpoken in mockage as men are wont to ſay in ſport, of a fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh and ignorant perſon, that he is apt <hi>as well</hi> in conditions <hi>as</hi> in knowledg, being apt indeed in neither of them both.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:46245:35"/>
There is alſo a doubt in the word <hi>Propitiable,</hi> whether it ſignify here that which taketh away ſin, or that which may be made available for the taking away of ſin; That is to ſay, whether it is to be taken in the active or in the paſſive ſignification.</p>
                  <p>Now the falſneſs of the Propoſition, after the meaning of the Schoolmen and the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and Impiety in that ſenſe which the words ſeem to import, is this; that they leaning to the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their fond Tranſubſtantiation, would make the quick and lively body of Chriſt's Fleſh (united and knit to the Divinity) to lye hid under the accidents, and outward ſhews of Bread and Wine. Which is very falſe, as I have ſaid before; and they building upon this foundation, do hold that the ſame Body is offered unto God, by the Prieſt in his dayly Maſſings, to put away the ſins of the quick and the dead; whereas by the Apoſtle to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> it is evident that there is but one Oblation, and one true and lively Sacrifice of the Church offered upon the Altar of the Croſs, which was, is, and ſhall be for ever the propitiation for the ſins of the whole World: and where there is Remiſſion of the ſame, there is, ſaith the Apoſtle, no more offering for ſin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Arguments confirming his Anſwer.</head>
                  <p>No Sacrifice ought to be done, but where the Prieſt is meet to offer <note place="margin">Ce-</note> the ſame.</p>
                  <p>All other Prieſts be unmeet to offer Sacrifice for ſin, but Chriſt alone. <note place="margin">la- rent.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> No other Prieſts ought to Sacrifice for ſin but Chriſt alone.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>The ſecond part of my Argument is thus proved.</head>
                  <p>No honour in God's Church ought to be taken where a man is not <note place="margin">Fe-</note> called as <hi>Aaron.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is a great honour in God's Church to Sacrifice for Sin: <note place="margin">ri- ſon.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Ergo.</p>
                  <p>No man ought to Sacrifice for Sin, but only they who are called.</p>
                  <p>But only Chriſt is called to that honour.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> No other Prieſt but Chriſt ought to Sacrifice for Sin.</p>
                  <p>That no man is called to this degree of Honour but Chriſt alone, it is evident; For there are but two only Orders of Prieſthood allowed in the Word of God: Namely, the Order of <hi>Aaron,</hi> and the Order of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech.</hi> But now the Order of <hi>Aaron</hi> is come to an end, by reaſon that it was unprofitable, and weak; and of the Order of <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech</hi> there is but one Prieſt alone, even Chriſt the Lord, who hath a Prieſthood that cannot paſs to any other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>An Argument.</head>
                  <p>That thing is in vain, and to no effect, where no neceſſity is <note place="margin">Ba-</note> wherefore it is done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:46245:36"/>
To offer up any more Sacrifice Propitiatory for the quick and the <note place="margin">ro-</note> dead, there is no neceſſity, for Chriſt our Saviour did that fully and perfectly once for all.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> To do the ſame in the Maſs, it is in vain. <note place="margin">co.</note>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Another Argument.</head>
                  <p>After that Eternal Redemption is found and obtained, there need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">Fe-</note> no more daily offering for the ſame.</p>
                  <p>But Chriſt coming an high Biſhop, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> found and obtained for us <note place="margin">ri-</note> Eternal Redemption.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> There needeth now no more daily Oblation for the Sins of <note place="margin">o.</note> the quick and the dead.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Another Argument.</head>
                  <p>All remiſſion of Sins cometh only by ſhedding of Blood. <note place="margin">Ca- meſ- tres.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the Maſs there is no ſhedding of Blood.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> In the Maſs there is no Remiſſion of Sins, and ſo it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth alſo that there is no Propitiatory Sacrifice.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Another Argument.</head>
                  <p>In the Maſs the Paſſion of Chriſt is not in verity, but in a Myſtery repreſenting the ſame; yea even there where the Lord's Supper is duly miniſtred. But where Chriſt ſuffereth not, there is he not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in verity: For the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Not that he might offer up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf oftentimes, (for then muſt he have ſuffered oftentimes ſince the beginning of the World.)</hi> Now where Chriſt is not offered, there is no Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Sacrifice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> In the Maſs there is no Propitiatory Sacrifice. <hi>For Chriſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared once in the latter end of the World to put ſin to flight by the offering up of himſelf. And as it is appointed to all men that they ſhall once dye, and then cometh the Judgment: even ſo Chriſt was once offered to take away the Sins of many. And unto them that look for him, ſhall he appear again without ſin unto ſalvation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="argument">
                  <head>Another Argument.</head>
                  <p>Where there is any Sacrifice that can make the comers thereunto <note place="margin">Da-</note> perfect, there ought men to ceaſe from offering any more Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piatory and Propitiatory Sacrifices.</p>
                  <p>But in the New Teſtament there is one only Sacrifice now already <note place="margin">ri-</note> long ſince offered, which is able to make the comers thereunto perfect for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ergo,</hi> In the New Teſtament they ought to ceaſe from offering <note place="margin">i.</note> any more Propitiatory Sacrifice.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sentences of the Scripture tending to the ſame end and purpoſe, out of which alſo may be gathered other manifeſt Arguments for more confirmation thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:46245:36"/>
                     <hi>By the which will</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>we are ſanctified by the offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>up of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt once for all.</hi> And in the ſame place; But this man, <hi>after that he had offered one Sacrifice for ſin, ſitteth for ever at the Right hand of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For with one Offering hath he made perfect for ever them that are ſanctified, and by himſelf hath he purged our Sins.</hi> I beſeech you to mark theſe words <hi>(by himſelf:)</hi> the which well weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will without doubt ceaſe all controverſie. The Apoſtle plainly denieth any other Sacrifice to remain for him that treadeth under his feet the Blood of the Teſtament, by the which he was made holy. Chriſt will not be crucified again, he will not his death to be had in deriſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He hath reconciled us in the Body of his Fleſh.</hi> Mark, I beſeech you, he <note place="margin">Col. 1.</note> ſaith not in the Myſtery of his Body; but <hi>in the Body of his Fleſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Jeſus Chriſt the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 John 2.</note> 
                     <hi>Righteous;</hi> and <hi>he is the Propitiation for our Sins; not for ours only, but for the Sins of the whole World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I know that all theſe places of the Scripture are avoided by two manner of ſubtil ſhifts: The one is, by the diſtinction of the bloody and unbloody Sacrifice; as tho our unbloody Sacrifice of the Church were any other than the Sacrifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, than a commemoration, a ſhewing forth, and a Sacramental Repreſentation of that one only bloody Sacrifice, offered up once for all.</p>
                  <p>The other is by depraving and wreſting the Sayings of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers unto ſuch a ſtrange kind of ſenſe, as the Fathers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indeed never meant. For what the meaning of the Fathers was, is evident by that which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writeth in his Epiſtle to <hi>Boniface,</hi> and in the 83d Chapter of his Ninth Book againſt <hi>Fauſtus the Manichee,</hi> beſides many other Places; likewiſe by <hi>Euſebius Emiſſenus, Cyprian, Chryſoſtom, Fulgentius, Bertram,</hi> and others, who do wholly concord and agree together in this unity in the Lord, that the Redemption, once made in Verity for the Salvation of Man, continueth in full ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect for ever, and worketh without ceaſing unto the end of the World; That the Sacrifice once offered cannot be conſumed; That the Lord's Death and Paſſion is as effectual, the vertue of that Blood once ſhed, as freſh at this day, for the waſhing away of ſins, as it was even the ſame day that it flowed out of the bleſſed Side of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: And finally, that the whole ſubſtance of our Sacrifice, which is frequented of the Church in the Lord's Supper, conſiſteth in Prayers, Praiſe, and giving of Thanks, and in remembring, and in ſhewing forth of that Sacrifice once offered upon the Altar of the Croſs; that the ſame might continually be had in reverence by Myſtery, which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:46245:37"/>
once only, and no more, was offered for the Price of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are the things (right worſhipful Mr. Prolocutor, and ye the reſt of the Commiſſioners) which I could preſently prepare to the anſwering of your three foreſaid Propheſies, being deſtitute of all help in this ſhortneſs of time, ſudden warning, and want of Books.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore I appeal to my firſt Proteſtation, moſt humbly deſiring the help of the ſame (as much as may be) to be granted unto me. And becauſe ye have lately given moſt unjuſt and cruel Sentence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, I do here appeal (ſo far forth as I may) to a more indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent and juſt cenſure and judgment of ſome other Superior, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent and Lawful Judge, and that according to the approved ſtate of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Howbeit, I confeſs, I am ignorant what that is at this preſent, through the trouble and alteration of the ſtate of the Realm. But if this Appeal may not be granted to me upon Earth, then do I fly (even as to my only Refuge and alone Haven of Health) to the Sentence of the Eternal Judge, that is, of the Almighty God, to whoſe moſt merciful Juſtice towards us, and moſt juſt Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifulneſs, I do wholly commit my ſelf, and all my Cauſe, nothing at all deſpairing of the Defence of my Advocate and alone Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to whom with the Everlaſting Father, and the Holy Spirit, the Sanctifier of us all, be now and for ever all Honour and Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ridley.</speaker>
                     <p>Of Chriſt's Real Preſence there may be a double under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding<hi>:</hi> 
                        <note place="margin">P. 56.</note> If you take the Real Preſence of Chriſt according to the Real and Corporal Subſtance which he took of the Virgin, that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence being in Heaven, cannot be on the Earth alſo. But if you mean a Real Preſence, <hi>ſecundum rem aliquam quae ad Corpus Chriſti pertinet: i. e.</hi> according to ſomething that appertaineth to Chriſt's Body, <hi>certes</hi> the Aſcenſion and abiding in Heaven are no let at all to that Preſence. Wherefore Chriſt's Body after that ſort is here preſent to us in the Lord's Supper, by Grace, I ſay, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> ſpeaketh it.</p>
                     <p>I grant the Bread to be converted and turned into the Fleſh of <note place="margin">P. 60.</note> Chriſt, but not by Tranſubſtantiation, but by a Sacramental Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion or turning. It is Transformed, ſaith <hi>Theophylact</hi> in the ſame place, by a Myſtical Benediction, and by the acceſſion or coming of the Holy Ghoſt unto the Fleſh of Chriſt. He ſaith not, by expulſion, or driving away the Subſtance of Bread, and by ſubſtituting or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in its place the Corporal Subſtance of Chriſt's Fleſh. And where he ſaith, <hi>It is not a Figure of the Body,</hi> we ſhould underſtand that ſaying, as he himſelf doth elſewhere add one, that is, it is no
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:46245:37"/>
naked or bare Figure only. For Chriſt is preſent in his Myſteries; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at any time, as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith, doth the Divine Majeſty abſent him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Divine Myſteries.</p>
                     <p>And I alſo worſhip Chriſt in the Sacrament, but not becauſe <note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 61.</note> he is included in the Sacrament: Like as I worſhip Chriſt alſo in the Scriptures, not becauſe he is really included in them. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I ſay, that the Body of Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament, but yet Sacramentally and Spiritually, according to his Grace giving Life, and in that reſpect really, that is according to his Benediction, giving Life.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore, I acknowledg gladly the true Body of Chriſt to be in the Lord's Supper in ſuch ſort as the Church of Chriſt (which is the Spouſe of Chriſt, and is taught of the Holy Ghoſt, and guided by God's Word) doth acknowledg the ſame. But the true Church of Chriſt doth acknowledg a Preſence of Chriſt's Body in the Lord's Supper, to be communicated to the Godly by Grace, and ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as I have often ſhewed, and by a Sacramental Signification, but not by the Corporal Preſence of the Body of his Fleſh.</p>
                     <p>We worſhip, I confeſs, the ſame true Lord and Saviour of <note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 65.</note> the world, which the Wiſe men worſhipped in the Manger; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit we do it in a Myſtery, and in the Sacrament of the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and that in Spiritual Liberty, as ſaith <hi>S. Aug. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de Doct. Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana,</hi> Not in carnal ſervitude; that is, we do not worſhip ſervilely the ſigns for the things; for that ſhould be, as he alſo ſaith, a part of a ſervile Infirmity; but we behold with the eyes of Faith him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent after Grace, and ſpiritually ſet upon the Table; and we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him who ſitteth above, and is worſhipped of the Angels; for Chriſt is always aſſiſtant to his Myſteries, as the ſaid <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith. And the Divine Majeſty, as ſaith <hi>Cyprian,</hi> doth never abſent it ſelf from the Divine Myſteries; but this Aſſiſtance and Preſence of Chriſt, as in Baptiſm, it is wholly Spiritual, and by Grace, and not by any Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Subſtance of the Fleſh: Even ſo it is here in the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, being rightly, and according to the Word of God duly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ridley.</speaker>
                     <p>My Proteſtation always ſaved, that by this mine <note place="margin">
                           <hi>P.</hi> 420.</note> Anſwer I do not condeſcend to your Authority, in that you are Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to the Pope; I anſwer thus,</p>
                     <p>In a ſenſe, the firſt Article is true, and in a ſenſe it is falſe; for if you take <hi>really</hi> for <hi>vere,</hi> for ſpiritually by Grace and Efficacy, then it is true that the Natural Body and Blood of Chriſt is in the Sacrament <hi>vere &amp; realiter,</hi> indeed and really; but if you take theſe terms ſo groſly,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:46245:38"/>
that you would conclude thereby a Natural Body, having Motion, to be contained under the Forms of Bread and Wine, <hi>vere &amp; realiter,</hi> then really is not Chriſt's Body and Blood in the Sacrament, no more than the Holy Ghoſt is in the Element of Water in our Baptiſm.</p>
                     <p>Becauſe this Anſwer was not underſtood, the Notaries wiſt not how to note it; wherefore the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> willed him to anſwer either Affirmatively or Negatively, either to grant the Article, or to deny it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, you know that where any Equivocation (which is a word having two ſignifications) is, except diſtinction be given, no direct Anſwer can be made; for it is one of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s Fallacies, containing two Queſtions under one, the which cannot be ſatisfied with one Anſwer. For both you and I agree herein, that in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament is the very true and Natural Body and Blood of Chriſt, even that which was born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> which aſcended into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which ſitteth on the Right Hand of God the Father, which ſhall come from thence to judg the quick and the dead; only we differ in <hi>modo,</hi> in the way and manner of being; we confeſs all one thing to be in the Sacrament, and diſſent in the manner of being there. I being fully by God's Word thereunto perſwaded, confeſs Chriſt's Natural Body to be in the Sacrament indeed by Spirit and Grace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that whoſoever receiveth worthily that Bread and Wine, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveth effectually Chriſt's Body, and drinketh his Blood; that is, he is made effectually Partaker of his Paſſion; and you make a groſſer kind of being, encloſing a Natural, a Lively, and a Moving Body, under the ſhape or form of Bread and Wine. Now this difference conſidered, to the Queſtion thus I anſwer, That in the Sacrament of the Altar is the Natural Body and Blood of Chriſt, <hi>vere &amp; realiter,</hi> indeed and really for ſpiritually by Grace and Efficacy; for ſo every worthy Receiver receiveth the very true Body of Chriſt; but if you mean really and indeed, ſo that thereby you would include a lively and a moveable Body under the forms of Bread and Wine, then in that ſenſe is not Chriſt's Body in the Sacrament really and indeed.</p>
                     <p>This Anſwer taken and penned of the Notaries, the Biſhop of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln</hi> propoſed the ſecond Queſtion or Article. To whom he anſwer'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rid.</speaker>
                     <p>Always my Proteſtation reſerved, I anſwer thus, That in the Sacrament is a certain Change, in that that Bread, which was before common Bread, is now made a lively preſentation of Chriſt's Body, and not only a Figure, but effectually repreſenteth his Body; that even as the Mortal Body was nouriſhed by that viſible Bread, ſo is the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:46245:38"/>
Soul fed with the Heavenly food of Chriſt's Body, which the eye of Faith ſeeth as the bodily eye ſeeth only Bread. Such a Sacramental mutation I grant to be in the Bread and Wine, which truly is no ſmall change, but ſuch a change as no mortal man can make, but only that <hi>Omnipotency of Chriſt's Word.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln</hi> willed him to anſwer directly either Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively or Negatively, without further Declaration of the Matter.</p>
                     <p>Then he Anſwered:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ridley.</speaker>
                     <p>That notwithſtanding the Sacramental Mutation of the which he ſpake, and all the Doctors confeſſed, the true Subſtance and Nature of Bread and Wine remaineth; with the which the Body is in like ſort nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed, as the Soul is by Grace and Spirit with the Body of Chriſt. Even ſo in Baptiſm the Body is waſhed with the viſible Water, and the Soul is cleanſed from all filth by the Inviſible Holy Ghoſt, and yet the Water cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not to be Water, but keepeth the nature of Water ſtill. In like ſort in the Sacrament of the Lords-Supper the Bread ceaſeth not to be Bread.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="analysis">
            <head>
               <hi>Extracts from Biſhop</hi> Poynets <hi>Diallaction.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will ſo divide the queſtion, that it may be briefly reduced to three heads. Firſt, I will ſhew that the true Body of Chriſt is given to the Faithful in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament; and that the words <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance,</hi> are not to be rejected, but that the Ancients treating of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did uſe them. In the next place, I will ſhew that there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the proper Body of Chriſt, and that which is preſent in the Sacrament, and that the Ancient Fathers thought ſo. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I will ſhew, what manner of Body this is, which is received in this Myſtery,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46245:39"/>
and why it is called by that Name, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Doctrine of the ſante Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>The Body of Chriſt is ſo called proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and improperly; properly, that Body which was taken of the Virgin. Improperly, as the Sacrament and the Church. That the Church is not properly the Body of Chriſt, cannot be doubted by any. It remains, that we now prove the ſame of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>It may eaſily be obſerved from what <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> writeth in this place, that that which Chriſt called his Body when he ſaid, <hi>Take, eat, this is my Body;</hi> and which be received together with his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, is in another manner his Body, than is his very proper Body, which was fed with that other. This did eat, that was eaten, and each is called his Body, but in a different manner.</p>
            <p>He gave the Sacrament of his Body, and not the Body it ſelf viſibly conceived, that is, his viſible Body; which is refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to his proper Body. But this Body, wherever it is, is viſible.</p>
            <p>It is to be obſerved, That the truth of the Lords Body may be ſpoken two ways, and ought to be underſtood two ways. For one verity of his Body is required in the Sacrament, another ſimply and out of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>As for what concerns our purpoſe, the very words of <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, how the Letter is not to be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed in thoſe things, which relate to this Myſtery; how far all carnal Senſe is to be removed, and all things to be referred to a ſpiritual Senſe; that with this Bread is preſent, the Divine Virtue, the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46245:39"/>
effect of Eternal Life; that the Divine Eſſence is infuſed; that the Words are Spirit and Life; that a ſpiritual Precept is delivered; that this Body, this Fleſh and Blood, this Subſtance of the Body ought not to be underſtood after a common manner, nor according to the Dictates of human Reaſon; but is ſo named, thought and believed, becauſe of certain eminent Effects, Virtues and Properties, which are joyned to it, which are naturally found in the Body and Blood of Chriſt, to wit, that it feed and quicken our Souls, and prepare our Bodies to Reſurrection and Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p>Here it is to be remembred, that the words are ſpiritual, and ſpiritually to be underſtood; that it is indeed named Fleſh and Blood, but that this ought to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the Spirit and Life, that is, of the lively Virtue of the Fleſh of our Lord, ſo that the Efficacy of Life is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred on the external Signs.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Theophylact</hi> ſaid, That the Bread is not the Figure of our Lords Body, he means that it is not only (or a bare) Figure of it.</p>
            <p>See how <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, That we are really, as I may ſo ſay, turned into the Fleſh of Chriſt. Yet who doth not ſee that this is a ſpiritual, not a carnal Converſion: So the Bread is really turned and tranſelementated into the Fleſh of Chriſt, but by a ſpiritual, not a carnal Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, inaſmuch as as the Bread obtains the Virtue of the Fleſh.</p>
            <p>How much better did <hi>Cyprian, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, Epiphanius, Emyſenus,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſpeak, who teach a like change to be performed in the Euchariſt, as is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in Baptiſm, by which the external
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46245:40"/>
Signs remain the ſame, and by Grace acquire a new ſubſtance in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>The Expoſition and Doctrine of <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram,</hi> concerning the Sacrament, ought in my Opinion to be diligently examined and embraced for two Reaſons.</p>
            <p>That this may appear more manifeſtly, and be remembred the better, I thought it not unfit to ſubjoyn from what I have already taught, a certain Compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Bodies of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The proper Body of Chriſt hath Head, Breaſt, and diſtinct Members; the myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body hath not. The proper Body hath Bones, Veins and Nerves; the myſtical Body hath not.</p>
            <p>That is organical; this is not.</p>
            <p>That is not a Figure; this is a Figure of the proper Body. That is human and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal by its Nature; this is Heavenly, Divine, and Spiritual.</p>
            <p>The matter of that is not ſubject to Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption; the material part of this is Bread, and is corrupted.</p>
            <p>That is contained in one place; this is preſent, whereſoever the Sacrament is cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated, but not, as in a place.</p>
            <p>That is not the Sacrament of another Body; this the Sacrament of another.</p>
            <p>That was taken of the Body of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and was once created; this is not taken of the Virgin, but is created daily by the myſtical Benediction potentially.</p>
            <p>That is a natural Body, this ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. Laſtly, That is ſimply, properly and abſolutely his Body; this in a certain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect only and improperly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:46245:40"/>
Nor is it enough here, if we flee one way of carnally underſtanding it, and fall upon another. For he who literally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands the eating of the Fleſh of Chriſt, and as altho it were a proper Speech, he is a carnal Capernaite; whether he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine it to be properly done this way, or that way. For it is probable that all the Capernaites underſtood Chriſt carnally, but not all the ſame way.</p>
            <p>For it is not therefore to be accounted a Spiritual ſenſe, becauſe they ſay the Fleſh of Chriſt is there inviſibly preſent. For if they mean his proper Fleſh, we do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not eat it carnally, becauſe we do not ſee it.</p>
            <p>Now in this Sacrament the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers obſerved two things, for each of which it might deſervedly be called and eſteemed the Body of Chriſt; but more eſpecially when it comprehends both. For the Bread is juſtly called his Body, as well becauſe it is the figure of his true Body, as becauſe it hath the lively vertue of it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to it, much more; but moſt eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, becauſe it comprehendeth both.</p>
            <p>It is therefore to be admired, what they mean, who will not ſuffer it to be called a figure, nor acknowledg any figure in the words of Inſtitution, but contumeliouſly call thoſe who own it, Figurative men, whereas it is manifeſt that all the Ancients did ſo call it. And indeed if there be no figure in it, it will be neither a ſign nor Sacrament. So that thoſe who traduce the maintainers of the other opinion as Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries, do indeed take away all Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from it.</p>
            <p>There is yet another thing, which the Ancient Fathers acknowledging to
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:46245:41"/>
be in this Sacrament, taught it to be truly the Body of our Lord; And that is the efficacious and lively vertue of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it ſelf, which is joyned with the Bread and Wine by Grace and Myſtical Benediction, and is called by divers names, although it be the ſame thing: by <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> the Intelligible, Inviſible and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Body: by <hi>Jerome</hi> the Divine and Spiritual Fleſh: by <hi>Irenaeus</hi> an Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thing: by <hi>Ambroſe</hi> the Spiritual Food and Body of the Divine Spirit: by others ſome other like thing. And this doth chiefly cauſe this Sacrament to be worthy of the appellation of his true Body and Blood, ſince it doth not only exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally bear the Image and Figure of it, but alſo carrieth along with it the inward and hidden natural propriety of the ſame Body; ſo that it cannot be eſteemed an empty Figure, or the ſign of a thing whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abſent, but the very Body of our Lord: Divine indeed and Spiritual, but preſent by Grace, full of vertue, powerful in effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy. For this is very frequent, that the names of things themſelves be aſcribed to their virtue and efficacy.</p>
            <p>The Fathers therefore in Treating of the Sacraments, uſe the words <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> not Philoſophically but Theologically: that is, they ſpeak not as natural Philoſophers, but as men diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Divine matters; they give the name of Nature and Subſtance to Grace, Virtue and Efficacy: the nature of the Sacrament ſo requiring.</p>
            <p>But this <hi>(that the Spiritual virtue is inſeparable from the Elements)</hi> is to be underſtood to be true, as long as the Sign ſerveth for that uſe, and is directed to that end, for which it was deſtined by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46245:41"/>
the Word of God. For if we apply it to other uſes, and abuſe it againſt the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Chriſt, it either is altogether not a Sacrament, or ceaſeth to be a Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>The dignity and due honour of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments is not injured, but remaineth whole and inviolate, while we confeſs both the truth of the Body, and the nature and ſubſtance of it, to be received by the Faithful, together with the Symbols: which alſo the ancient Fathers teſtifie to be done. And then this diſtinction which alſo thoſe Fathers diligently obſerved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing received between that proper or aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Body of the Lord, and this Symboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Body, or Sacrament of the Body, the analogy of our Faith is not violated, which no ways ought to be ſhaken: ſince we attribute to each Body his peculiar pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties. For we ſay that the proper and aſſumed Body is in a place, and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed with a ſpace, by reaſon of the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> of a true Body, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All men ſee, that we alſo here affirm the Subſtance to be preſent, and aſſert our Communion with Chriſt naturally, and as I may ſay, ſubſtantially. But then theſe words ought to be underſtood after the manner not of Philoſophers but of Divines. Neither ſhould we quarrel about the term of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> although barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and not in the leaſt neceſſary: Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they meant thereby ſuch a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of Subſtances, as the Ancients taught: that is, a Sacramental one: ſuch as is alſo performed in a man regenerated by Baptiſm, who is made a new man, and a new creature. Such as is alſo performed when we are converted into the Fleſh of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:46245:42"/>
Chriſt, which examples the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers uſed.</p>
            <p>If any here require a Miracle (for ſome Fathers call the Euchariſt a great Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle) it is in truth no leſs wonderful, that Bread and Wine, which are earthly Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and apt only to nouriſh the Body, ſhould by virtue of the Myſtical Benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on obtain that inward force, and ſuch powerful efficacy, as to cleanſe, nouriſh, ſanctifie, and prepare to immortality both our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, and to make us the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and one Body with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="analysis">
            <head>
               <hi>Diallacticon Viri boni &amp; literati de veritate, natura atque ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia corporis &amp; ſanguinis Chriſti in Euchariſtia. Ad cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Becae Opuſculorum, Vol.</hi> II. <hi>Par.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 31. <hi>Genevae,</hi> 1573. <hi>f.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CAuſam ita partiri placuit, ut ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matim ad tria capita revocetur. Primò oſtendam veritatem corporis Chriſti in Euchariſtia dari fidelibus; nec has voces Naturam at que Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiam fugiendas eſſe, ſed Veteres de hoc Sacramento diſſerentes ita lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutos fuiſſe Deinde diſcrimen eſſe monſtrabo inter corpus Domini pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium, &amp; illud quod ineſt in Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento; vetereſque Patres ita cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe. Poſtremo cujuſmodi ſit hoc Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, quod accipitur in Myſterio, &amp; cur eo nomine cenſeatur, indicabo,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:46245:39"/>
ſecundum eorundem Patrum ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam, <hi>p.</hi> 33, 34.</p>
            <p>Corpus Chriſti dicitur propriè &amp; impropriè; propriè, Corpus illud ſumptum ex Virgine; impropriè, ut Sacramentum &amp; Eccleſia. Quod Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia propriè Corpus Chriſti non ſit, nemini dubium eſt; de Sacramento reſtat, ut nunc idem Probemus, <hi>p.</hi> 38.</p>
            <p>Non difficile eſt animadvertere ex his quae ſcribit hoc loco Chryſoſtomus, aliter eſſe Corpus, quod Chriſtus ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe Corpus ſuum appellavit, cum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceret, Accipite, edite; hoc meum eſt Corpus, quod ipſe quoque ſimul ſume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat cum diſcipulis; aliter ipſum Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus proprium, quod illo altero veſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur. Hoc comedebat, illud comeſum eſt; &amp; utrumque Corpus, ſed diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa ratione, dicitur, <hi>p.</hi> 39.</p>
            <p>Sacramentum videlicet Corporis (dedit) &amp; non ipſum viſibiliter, ſive viſibile Corpus, quod ad proprium Corpus refertur. Hoc autem Corpus ubicunque eſt, viſibile eſt, <hi>p.</hi> 40.</p>
            <p>Obſervandum eſt veritatem Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nici Corporis, dup citer dici ac debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re dupliciter acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i. Alia namque veritas Corporis requiritur in Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, alia ſimpliciter &amp; abſque Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, <hi>p.</hi> 41.</p>
            <p>Quod ad noſtrum inſtitutum atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, ipſa Cypriani verba ſatis indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, quam non ſequenda ſit litera in his quae de hoc Myſterio dicuntur, quam procul arcendus eſt carnis Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp; ad Senſum ſpiritualem omnia referenda; huic Pani Divinae Virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis praeſentiam adeſſe, Vitae Aeternae
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:46245:39"/>
effectum, Divinam inſundi eſſentiam verba Spiritum &amp; vitam eſſe, ſpirituale documentum tradi, hoc Corpus, hunc ſanguinem, &amp; carnem hanc ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Corporis, non communi more, nec ut humana ratio dictat accipi oportere, ſed ita nominari, exiſtimari, credi, propter eximios quoſdam Effectus, Virtutes, &amp; Proprietates conjunctas, quae Corpori &amp; ſanguini Chriſti na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura inſunt; nempe quod paſcat ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas noſtras, &amp; vivificet ſimul, &amp; Corpora ad Reſurrectionem &amp; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitatem praeparet, <hi>p.</hi> 46.</p>
            <p>Hic cogitandum eſt verba ſpiritua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia eſſe, &amp; ſpiritualiter intelligenda; carnem quidem &amp; ſanguinem nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari, ſed de Spiritu &amp; Vitâ, id eſt, vivificâ Dominicae carnis Virtute de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere intelligi, &amp; proinde vim Vitae ſignis externis inditam eſſe, <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theophylactus quum dicit (panem) non eſſe Figuram (Corporis Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nici) ſenſit non tantum Figuram eſſe, <hi>p.</hi> 47.</p>
            <p>Ecce Chryſoſtomus dicit, realiter ut ita loquar, nos converti in carnem Chriſti, ſed ſpiritualem illam non carnalem Converſionem eſſe quis non videt? Ita reipsâ convertitur &amp; tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elementatur Panis in carnem Chriſti, ſed ſpirituali non carnali Converſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, quia Panis virtutem carnis aſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitur, <hi>p.</hi> 48.</p>
            <p>Quanto melius locuti ſunt Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus, Ambroſius, Epiphanius, Emy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenus, &amp; alii, qui ſimilem Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationem in Euchariſtiâ cum ea quae fit in Baptiſmo confirmant quâ fit ut
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:46245:40"/>
ſigna maneant eadem, &amp; per grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am novam acquirant ſubſtantiam ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militer, <hi>p.</hi> 49.</p>
            <p>Cujus ego viri (Bertrami) Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem &amp; de Sacramento viam di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputandi duas ob cauſas diligenter expendendam &amp; amplectendam arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tror, <hi>p.</hi> 52.</p>
            <p>Quod ut magis appareat, &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriâ reponatur, non inutile fore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tavi, ex his quae ſupra memoravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> quandam per collatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſubjungere.</p>
            <p>Corpus Chriſti proprium habet caput, pectus, membra dinſtincta, Corpus myſticum non habet. Corpus proprium habet Oſſa, Venas, Nervos, myſticum non habet.</p>
            <p>Illud organicum eſt; hoc non eſt.</p>
            <p>Illud Figura non eſt; hoc eſt Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gura proprii Corporis. Illud naturâ ſuâ humanum &amp; corporeum eſt; hec Coeleſte, Divinum, Spirituale.</p>
            <p>Illius materia Corruptioni non eſt obnoxia; hujus pars materialis Panis eſt, &amp; corrumpitur.</p>
            <p>Illud uno loco continetur; hoc, ubicunque Sacramentum celebratur, adeſt, at non ut in loco.</p>
            <p>Illud non eſt Sacramentum alterius Corporis; hoc Sacramentum eſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius.</p>
            <p>Illud de Virginis Mariae corpore ſumptum, ſemel creatum eſt; hoc de Virgine non ſumitur ſed quotidie per Benedictionem myſticam potentiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter creatur.</p>
            <p>Illud naturale Corpus eſt; hoc ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturale. Denique illud ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer, hoc ſecundum quid; illud pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priè &amp; abſolute, hoc improprie Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus eſt, <hi>p.</hi> 52, 53.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:46245:40"/>
Neque hic ſatis eſt, ſi modum unum carnaliter intelligendi fugiamus, &amp; in alium impingamus. Nam qui Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti carnem edere ſecundum literam accipit, &amp; quaſi locutio propria ſit; is Capernaita carnalis eſt; ſive id hoc ſive illo modo proprie fieri putat.—Nam veriſimile eſt, Carpernaitas om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes quidem carnaliter intellexiſſe, ſed non omnes eodem modo, <hi>p.</hi> 53.</p>
            <p>Non enim ideo ſpiritualis ſenſus exiſtimandus eſt, quia dicunt carnem Chriſti inviſibiliter adeſſe; nam ſi de propria carne intelligant, non ideo carnaliter non edimus, quia non vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demus, <hi>p.</hi> 54.</p>
            <p>Jam in hoc Sacramento veteres Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres duas res animadverterunt; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quas ſingulas merito corpus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti diceretur &amp; haberetur, maximè verò cùm utramque comprehendat, Nam &amp; quia figura veri corporis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eſt, jure corpus appellatur; &amp; quia virtutem ejuſdem vitalem conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam habet, multò magis; tum verò maximè quòd utrumque complecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Quò magis mirandum eſt, quid illis in mentem veniat, qui figuram non patiantur appellari, nec figuram in Coenae verbis agnoſcant; ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s qui agnoſcunt, per contumeliam figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores appelant cùm tamen manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum ſit Veteres omnes ſic appelláſſe. Quòd ſi figura non erit, nec Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, nec Sacramentum erit. Itaque. qui in illos tanquam Sacramentarios dicere parati ſunt, ipſi omnino Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta tollunt. <hi>p.</hi> 55.</p>
            <p>Alterum eſſe diximus, quod vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Patres agnoſcentes in hoc Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:46245:41"/>
verè Dominicum corpus eſſe voluerunt. Eſt autem virtus ipſius corporis efficax &amp; vivifica, quae per gratiam &amp; myſticam benedictionem cum pane &amp; vino conjungitur, &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis nominibus appellatur, cùm res eadem ſit; ab Auguſtino corpus intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligibile, inviſibile, ſpirituale; ab Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronymo caro divina &amp; ſpiritualis; ab Irenaeo res coeleſtis; ab Ambroſio eſca ſpiritualis, &amp; corpus divini ſpiritus; ab aliis aliud ſimile quippiam. Et hoc multo etiam magis efficit, ut hoc Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum digniſſimum ſit veri cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris &amp; ſanguinis nomenclaturâ: quum non ſolum extrinſecus imaginem &amp; figuram ejus prae ſe ferat verùm; etiam intus abditam &amp; latentem naturalem ejuſdem corporis proprietatem, hoc eſt, vivificam virtutem ſecum trahat; ut jam non inanis figura, aut abſentis omnino rei ſignum exiſtimari poſſit, ſed ipſum corpus Domini, divinum quidem &amp; ſpirituale, ſed praeſens gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiâ, plenum virtute, potens efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. Saepe autem fit, ut nomina re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ipſarum tribuantur earum vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti &amp; efficacitati. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cum agitur de Sacramentis, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem faciunt Patres Naturae &amp; Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiae, non <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hoc eſt, non ut Philoſophi naturales loquuntur, ſed homines de divinis rebus diſſerentes, gratiae, virtuti, &amp; efficacitati naturae ſubſtantiaeque no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men impertientes, nimirum Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti naturâ id poſtulante, <hi>p.</hi> 57.</p>
            <p>Hoc autem <hi>(inſeparabilitas virtutis ſpiritualis ab Elementis)</hi> ita intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt, quamdiu ſignum ei ſervit uſui &amp; fini accommodatur, cui juxta verbum Dei deſtinatum fuerit. Nam
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:46245:41"/>
ſi ad alios uſus applicamus, &amp; abuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur contra Chriſti inſtitutum: aut Sacramentum prorſus non eſt, aut Sacramentum eſſe deſinit, <hi>p.</hi> 64.</p>
            <p>Sacramentorum dignitas &amp; debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus honos non laeditur, ſed integer &amp; inviolatus manet; dum &amp; veritatem corporis &amp; naturam ac ſubſtantiam illius unâ cum ſymbolis accipi fatea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur à fidelibus, quod &amp; veteres Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres fieri teſtantur. Deinde hâc recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ, quam iidem Patres diligenter ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervarunt, diſtinctione inter propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſive aſſumptum illud corpus Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, &amp; hoc ſymbolicum corpus ſive Sacramentum corporis, non peccatur in analogiam fidei noſtrae, quae nullo pacto convellenda eſt: quandoquidem utrique corpori quae ſua ſunt attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imus. Proprium enim &amp; aſſumptum corpus in loco eſſe &amp; loci ſpatio cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribi dicimus, propter veri cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris modum ut ait Auguſtinus, <hi>&amp;c. Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vident ſubſtantiam quoque à nobis (in hoc libro) praeſentem affirmari, &amp; communionem noſtram cum Chriſto naturaliter, &amp; ut ita dicam, ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tialiter praedicari: ſed has voces, non ut Philoſophi, ſed ut Theologi lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quuntur, intelligi oportere. Nec de Tranſubſtantiationis vocabulo, quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis barbaro minimeque neceſſario, liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garemus, ſi modò talem ſubſtantiarum tranſmutationem interpretentur, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Veteres agnoſcebant, Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talem videlicet, qualis etiam in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine fit per Baptiſmum regenerato, qui novus homo factus eſt, &amp; nova creatura: qualis etiam fit, quum nos
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:46245:42"/>
in Chriſti carnem convertimur: qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Patres antiqui utebantur exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plis, <hi>p.</hi> 65.</p>
            <p>Quòd ſi nonnulli miraculum requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt (nam Patres aliquot Euchariſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ingens miraculum nominant) non minus profectò mirandum eſt panem &amp; vinum creaturas terrenas, &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pori tantùm paſcendo natas, eam vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute benedictionis myſticae vim inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, adeòque potentem efficacitatem obtinere, ut &amp; animos &amp; corpora mundent, alant, ſanctificent, atque ad immortalitatem praeparent, ut nos membra Chriſti &amp; unum cum illo corpus conficiant. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:46245:42"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
